<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The perfect major shewing the easiest way of handling arms, the millitary motions, with the manner how to enter into a field, and to form a batallion. By F. d' Morains, formerly an officer in the French army's [sic]. Licensed April the 24th. 1686. Ro. L'Estrange.</title>
            <author>Morains, François de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2613D</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217864</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829507</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829507</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1920:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The perfect major shewing the easiest way of handling arms, the millitary motions, with the manner how to enter into a field, and to form a batallion. By F. d' Morains, formerly an officer in the French army's [sic]. Licensed April the 24th. 1686. Ro. L'Estrange.</title>
                  <author>Morains, François de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 183, [3]  p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by B. Griffin for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In French and English, on facing pages.</note>
                  <note>French title page (A1v) reads: Le major parfait.</note>
                  <note>With a final contents leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Drill and minor tactics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="fre">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33947:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33947:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>LE MAJOR PARFAIT, QUI ENSEIGNE AVEC FACILITE' LE MANIMENT DES ARMES, LES EVOLUTIONS MILITAIRES, Avec la maniere d'entrer dans le Champ de Battaille, &amp; fermer LE BATAILLON.</p>
                  <p>Par <hi>F. De Morains,</hi> cy-devant, Officier dans les Armées de France.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Permis d'Imprimer le</hi> 24. Avril 1686.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Signé</hi> Ro. Leſtrange.</p>
                  <p>A LONDRES, Chés <hi>B. Griffin,</hi> pour l'Auteur.
1686.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33947:3"/>
                  <head>AU ROY.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIRE,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>LA naturelle &amp; incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble douceur de VOTRE MAJESTE' qui reçoit les humbles offres des Etrangers, comme de ſes veritables Sujets, m'a fait oſer prendre la liberté de vous conſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crer ce Diſcours militaire, qui traite briévement, le plus relevé, le plus haſardeux, &amp; le plus difficile ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jet du monde, le Métier des No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, la Pratique des Courageux, <pb facs="tcp:33947:4"/>&amp; l'Exercice des Princes, &amp; des Rois: Métier auquel, pour acque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rir de la gloire, il convient faire tout enſemble, la Maîtriſe, &amp; l'Apprentiſſage: Car il faut vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre en apprenant, &amp; apprendre en vainquant. Ce Diſcours contient ce que les plus experimentez, du paſſé nous récitent ſur ce ſujet; ce qu'en ce temps j'ay oüi dire, &amp; vû pratiquer aux plus braves Guerriers, que ce ſiécle ait produit parmi les plus belliqueuſes Nations du monde, qui eſt une bonne caution pour la certitude de ce Diſcours, mais non pas ſi ſuffiſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te que l'expérience qu'en a VO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRE MAJESTE', s'étant treuvée en perſonne en pluſieurs rencon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres <pb facs="tcp:33947:5"/>vigoureuſes, à la tête des Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mées, où Elle s'eſt expoſeé comme ſi Elle avoit été immortelle: Ce qui fait l'admiration de toute l'Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, &amp; la crainte des Ennemis de VOTRE MAJESTE', Faſſe le Ciel qu'Elle y excelle de telle ſorte, que les plus généreux Guerriers la re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doutent, &amp; ne veüillent rechercher dans les Hiſtoires d'autres exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, que ceux de vos valheureux Exploits. Enfin, Sire, ſi je pouvois tout dire, au lieu d'une Epiſtre, je ferois un Panégirique mais les pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roles me manquent. Je ſupplie tres-humblement VOTRE MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTE', de me pardonner la liberté que je prens de vous preſenter ce Diſcours, &amp; de me permettre de <pb facs="tcp:33947:6"/>laiſſer dans le ſilence tout ce que je ne puis exprimer. Il y a quel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques fois beaucoup d'Art à ſe taire &amp; le ſilence étoit vn grand My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere chez les Anciens. C'eſt pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoy, Sire, je me tais, en de man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant la Protection de VOTRE, MAJESTE', &amp; la grace de me permettre de prendre la liberté de me dire, avec le plus profond reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>SIRE</salute>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>De VOTRE MAJESTE',</hi> Le tres Humble, tres-Obeiſſent &amp; tres-fideles Serviteur. <hi>F. DE MORAINS.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33947:7"/>
                  <head>AVIS AU LECTEUR.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Ami Lecteur,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>JE ne doute pas qu'il ne ſe trouve bien des envieux, qui ne m'accuſent de té<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merité, d'avoir pris la liberté de conſacrer ce diſcours à vn ſi grand Monarque: Mais quand ils prendront garde du Sujet du Livre, &amp; la neceſſité qu'il y a pour la conſervation d'un Royaume, que les Troupes ſçachent leur devoir, ils pourront rendre quelque ſorte de juſtice au zéle, qui m'a porté à le mettre au jour, puis qu'il n'eſt fait que pour apprendre avec facilité le Maniment des Armes, les Evolutions Militaires, avec la maniére d'entre, dans le Champ de Battaille, former le Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taillon, tirer en Retraite, &amp; en la garde d'un Paſſage, ou Chemin creux, &amp; dans les Défilez. <pb facs="tcp:33947:8"/>Eufin, Lecteur, je vous donne cette Inſtruction de la maniére dont on fait la Guerre à pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſuivant que je l'ay vû, &amp; l'ay pratiqué en ces derniéres Campagnes, que je preſente du meilleur de mon coeur à toute la Nobleſſe, qui a toûjonrs tenu à grand honneur de porter les Armes pour le Service de leurs Rois, &amp; pour la gloire de leur Patrie, pour leſquels ils ſont obligez de répandre leur ſang. Si ceux qui veulent ſuivre ce glorienx Métier y peuvent apprendre quelque choſe, je m'eſtimeray l'hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me du Monde le plus heureux de voir que mon travail ne ſoit pas inutile. <hi>Adieu</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="French" type="version">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33947:9"/>
                  <head>LE MAJOR PARFAIT, <hi>Qui enſeigne avec facilité, le mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment des Armes, les Evolutions Militaires, avec la maniére d'en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trer dans le Champ de Battaille, &amp; former le Battaillon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Le Devoir du Major.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div n="1" type="duty">
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <p>LE Major doit prendre la Colonelle avec ſon Aide Major, ou celuy qui en fait la charge, laquelle il doit conduire dans le Champ de Battaille, qu'il aura reconnu.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="duty">
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:33947:10"/>
                        <head>2</head>
                        <p>Le Major doit recevoir les Mouſquetaires, faire &amp; regler le front du Battaillon.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="duty">
                        <head>3.</head>
                        <p>L' Aide Major doit être à la lête des Picquiers, leſquels il réglera de la même maniére, derriére les Mouſquetaires, à vingt pas de diſtance, s'il ſe trove aſſez de Terrain pour cela.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="duty">
                        <head>4.</head>
                        <p>Le Major, ou Aide Major, doit obſerver que la diſtance des files, lors qu'on ne fait point d'Exercice, doit avoir un demi pas de diſtance: &amp; lors qu'on veut faire, le ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niment des Armes, ou les Evolutions, on les fait ouvir à un pas de diſtance.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="duty">
                        <head>5.</head>
                        <p>Aucune Compagnie ne doit entrer dans le Champ de Battaille, que dans ſon rang: &amp; les Files réglées à ſix de hauteur.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="duty">
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:33947:11"/>
                        <head>6.</head>
                        <p>Les Capitaines, ou Officiers doivent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duire leurs Compagnies la Picque à la main. Les Lieutenans ſeront à la queüe des Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiers, lors qu'il y aura des Enſeignes: mais quand il n'y en aura point, ils ſe mettront à la tête des Picquiers lors qu'on les ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gera en Battaille.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="duty">
                        <head>7.</head>
                        <p>Les Compagnies arrivan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> dans le Champ de Battaille défileront conſécutivement, &amp; iront paſſer ſur l'aîle gauche des Picquiers, &amp; auparavant laiſſeront leurs Picques dans le Champ de Battaille, &amp; les Mouſquetaires ſuivront leur marche juſqu'à ce qu'ils ayent joint le front des Mouſquetaires.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="duty">
                        <head>8</head>
                        <p>Au moment que la derniére Compagnie aura joint le Battaillon, l'Aide Major doit faire défiler les Picquiers par quatre de rang, pour aller joindre le Battaillon ſur le même <pb n="8" facs="tcp:33947:12"/>front des Mouſquetaires ſur l'aîle gauche, &amp; ſans perdre temps, auſſi tôt le dernier quart de rangs arrivé, il fera faire à gauche au demi rang de la gauche des Mouſquetaires, &amp; à droit aux Picquiers, en faiſant le Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, <hi>March.</hi> Les Picquiers, &amp; les Mouſquetaires occuperont le même Terrain aprés quoy il faut faire le commandement, <hi>Remettez vous.</hi> Il faut faire que dans ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouvement il y ait toûjours, un Sergent à l'aîle de châque rang, pour empêcher qu'il ne ſe fauſſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="duty">
                        <head>9.</head>
                        <p>Aucun Officier ne doit quitter la tête de ſa Compagnie, ni la Picque, que le Battaillon ne ſoit formé.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="duty">
                        <head>10.</head>
                        <p>Auſſi tôt qu'un Battaillon eſt formé le prémier Lieutenant reſtera à la queuë de la prémiére aîle des Mouſquetaires, le der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier à la queuë de l'aîle gauche, un Enſeigne à la queuë des Picquiers, avec la moitié <pb n="10" facs="tcp:33947:13"/>des Sergens, pour empêcher que les Soldats ne rompent leurs rangs, &amp; ne ſe débandent.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="duty">
                        <head>11.</head>
                        <p>Lors que le Major fera quelque Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, les Officiers, &amp; Sergens doivent faire obſerver le ſilence, &amp; nul autre que lui ne doit faire aucun Commandement, ſi ce n'eſt celui qui commande le Régi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="duty">
                        <head>12.</head>
                        <p>Les Capitaines &amp; Officiers ſeront em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployez à l'exécution des Evolutions, ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant la diſpoſition qu'en fera le Major.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="duty">
                        <head>13.</head>
                        <p>Les Tambours ſeront poſtez ſur les aîles.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="14" type="duty">
                        <head>14.</head>
                        <p>Il eſt bon que les Officiers prennnent garde que les Soldats ne ſe négligent en aucune choſe qui regarde le ſervice; comme de bien garder leurs rangs, porter lours <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33947:14"/>Armes, obſerver leurs diſtances, non pas mê<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me dans le Battaillon, mais dans les moindres choſes, comme en marchant en Campagne, villes, ou Villages, ou étants en Sentinelle; car nous voyons ſouvent des Soldats porter leurs Armes tantôt ſur une épaule, &amp; tantôt ſur l'autre, &amp; même ſous le bras, ce qu'on ne doit pas ſouffrir ſans cauſe légitime; car qui néglige les petites choſes, ne ſe ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie guéres des grandes avec le temps, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce que la négligence ſe tourne en habitude: pour cét effet, les bas Officiers doivent viſiter les Armes de leurs Soldats, pour voir ſi elles ſont en état: &amp; au cas qu'elles ne le ſoient pas, aprés les avoir avertis, il faut les faire raccommoder &amp; nettoyer à leurs depens: ce qu'ils pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roient faire eux mêmes s'ils étoient vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans, &amp; ce qui eſt la marque d'un bon Soldat. Il eſt bon que les Capitaines ne s'en rapportent pas tout à fait à leurs bas Officiers: Ils doivent faire de temps en temps la revuë de leurs Compagnies, &amp; en même temps de leurs Arms: &amp; au cas <pb n="14" facs="tcp:33947:15"/>qu'ils ne les trouvent pas comme il faut; aprés avoir commandé aux Sergens d'y avoir ſoin, il faut les faire raccommoder aux dépens de tous les bas Officiers: On n'aura pas fait cela une fois, qu'on verra châcun faire ſon devoir ſelon ſon état; car il faut avoir dans les Troupes de la ſubordination.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. II. <hi>La maniére; &amp; les termes d'un Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taillon, avec une méthode facile pour apprendre les Evolutions mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litaires.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div n="forming a battalion" type="commands">
                        <head>PREMIEREMENT.</head>
                        <p>LES termes d'un Bataillon, quarré d'hommes,</p>
                        <p>Le Battaillon eſt compoſé de Chefs de Files, ſerres de Files, de chefs de demie files, ſerres de demies Files, Files de main droite, &amp; Files de main gauche.</p>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33947:16"/>
                        <p>Le devant du Battaillon s'apelle Tête ou Front.</p>
                        <p>Le derriére s'apelle queüe.</p>
                        <div n="commands" type="explanation">
                           <head>L'expliiation s'enſuit La maniére &amp; les termes d'un battaillon.</head>
                           <div n="1" type="command">
                              <head>1.</head>
                              <p>La premiére File d'un Battaillon eſt celle qui en tient la main droite, ſur laquelle tous les autres doivent ſe dreſſer,</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="2" type="command">
                              <head>2.</head>
                              <p>File eſt faire que les ſoldats ſoient der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riére les uns des autres directement, &amp; tous les autres à droite ligne, de telle ſorte que pas un Soldat n'avance ni à droite ni à gauche.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="3" type="command">
                              <head>3.</head>
                              <p>Pour ſe bien dreſſer, chaque Soldat en ſa File regardera à droit &amp; à gauche ſon chef de File, &amp; ne panchera le corps d'aucun côte.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="4" type="command">
                              <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33947:17"/>
                              <head>4.</head>
                              <p>Dreſſer les rangs, eſt faire que les Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dats de châque rang ſoient directement poſtez les uns aux côtez l'un de l'autre, &amp; tous d'un Front, ſans que pas un Soldat ne ſoit trop avancé, ni trop en arriére.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="5" type="command">
                              <head>5</head>
                              <p>Pour ſe bien dreſſer, tous ceux de châque rang regarderont devant &amp; derriére celui qui tient la main droite, ſans partir de leurs places: Ou bien; comme nous enſeignerons cy-aprés, on fera un quart de tour à droit ou à gauche, puis on ſe dreſſera ſelon l'or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre du troiſiéme Article.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="6" type="command">
                              <head>6.</head>
                              <p>La hauteur des Battaillons pour combat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre doit être de Six hommes; mais lors qu'on veut faire l'exercice plus particulié<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rement, il y en faut mettre huit, pour avoir des quarts de Files.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="7" type="command">
                              <pb n="20" facs="tcp:33947:18"/>
                              <head>7.</head>
                              <p>La hauteur du Battaillon eſt diviſée en deux quarts de File, l'un s'apelle quart de File de la tête; &amp; l'autre de la queüe; autrement, les quarts de File de dehors; &amp; les autres, les quarts de File du milieu.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="8" type="command">
                              <head>8.</head>
                              <p>Lors que le Soldat tourne, il doit toûjours tourner ſur un même pied, qui eſt d'ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naire, le gauche, aſin d'obſerver les di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: Et lors qu'il change de place, il doit toûjours commencer à partir du pied droit.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="9" type="command">
                              <head>9.</head>
                              <p>Si le Soldat, veut marcher en arriére, il doit faire demy tour à droit.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="10" type="command">
                              <head>10.</head>
                              <p>Faire à droite c'eſt faire un quart de tour vers la main droite, &amp; sarreſter,</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="11" type="command">
                              <head>11.</head>
                              <p>Faire à gauche, c'eſt faire un quart de tour vers la main gauche.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="12" type="command">
                              <pb n="22" facs="tcp:33947:19"/>
                              <head>12.</head>
                              <p>Faire demi tour à droit, c'eſt faire un demy tour vers la main droite, de façon qu'on ait devant ſoy celui qui au paravant étoit der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riére.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="13" type="command">
                              <head>13.</head>
                              <p>Faire demy tour à gauche, c'eſt faire demy tour vers la main gauche, ſe trouvant en la façon précédente.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="14" type="command">
                              <head>14.</head>
                              <p>Il faut remarquer que lors qu'on fait un Commandement ſans s'expliquer, ce doit toûjours être en avant.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="15" type="command">
                              <head>15.</head>
                              <p>Il faut, faiſant à Droite, ou demy tour à droite, ſe remettre par gauche: &amp; faiſant à gauche, ou demi tour à gauche, ſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mettre par droit, &amp; avoir toûjours ſoin de ſe dreſſer.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="16" type="command">
                              <pb n="24" facs="tcp:33947:20"/>
                              <head>16.</head>
                              <p>Doubler les rangs à droite, c'eſt faire que le ſecond rang avance dans le prémier; le quatre dans le trois; le ſixiéme dans le cinquiéme; &amp; ainſi par ordre prendre la main droite de ceux derriére leſquels ils ſont en ſe joignant, &amp; ſeront rangez comme cy-devant: Sinon, deux n'en feront qu'un.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="17" type="command">
                              <head>17.</head>
                              <p>Doubler les rangs à gauche, c'eſt faire ſelon qu'il eſt dit cy-deſſus; que le ſecond rang entre dans le prémier: mais au lieu de main droite, c'eſt par la gauche.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="18" type="command">
                              <head>18.</head>
                              <p>Doubler les rangs à droite par demies files, c'eſt faire que les demies files Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chent en avant, &amp; paſſent entre les ſerres de demies files, ſe joignant châcun chef de demie file à la main droite.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="19" type="command">
                              <pb n="26" facs="tcp:33947:21"/>
                              <head>19.</head>
                              <p>Doubler les rangs à gauche par demie files, il faut marcher en avant, &amp; ſuivre comme cy-devant, prenant la main gauche, de châque chef de demie file de ceux qui les doivent ſuivre.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="20" type="command">
                              <head>20.</head>
                              <p>Se reméttre, eſt reprendre la même place qu'on avoit auparavant.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="21" type="command">
                              <head>21.</head>
                              <p>Ayant doublé les rangs ſimplement, ou par demie file à droite, il faudra quand ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant des rangs cù ils ſont, faiſant demi tour à droite &amp; ayant repris leurs places à la di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance premiére, ils facent demi tour à droit &amp; ayant doublé à gauche ſimplement, ou par demie file, il faudra qu'en ſortant des rangs où il ſont, ils facent demi tour à droite, &amp; leur diſtance étant priſe, ils feront demitour à gauche, &amp; ſe faiſant châcun ſe trouvera der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riére celui qui auparavant merchoit devant lui</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="22" type="command">
                              <pb n="28" facs="tcp:33947:22"/>
                              <head>22.</head>
                              <p>Doubler les files, à droite, c'eſt faire que la ſeconde file de main droite ſe joigne à la premiére, &amp; de deux n'en face qu'une; ſemblablement, la quatriéme à la troiſiéme, la ſixiéme à la cinquiéme, &amp; ainſi des autres par ordre, tant qu'il y aura de files.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="23" type="command">
                              <head>23.</head>
                              <p>Doubler les files à gauche, c'eſt faire que la deuxiéme file de main gauche ſe joigne à la premiére, la quatriéme à la troiſiéme, la ſixiéme à la cinquiéme, &amp; le tout avec l'ordre que cy-deſſus.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="24" type="command">
                              <head>24.</head>
                              <p>Ouvrir les rangs, c'eſt faire que la diſtance des rangs ſoit plus grande.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="25" type="command">
                              <head>25.</head>
                              <p>Serrer les rang, c'eſt faire que la diſtance des rangs ſoit moins grande.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="26" type="command">
                              <pb n="30" facs="tcp:33947:23"/>
                              <head>26.</head>
                              <p>On fait ouvrir les rangs en trois diverſes maniéres: à ſçavoir, en avant. en arriere, &amp; en avant &amp; en arriere tout à la fois, &amp; ſouvent à double diſtance.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="27" type="command">
                              <head>27.</head>
                              <p>Ouvrir les rangs en avant à double di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, c'eſt faire que tous les rangs s'avan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent en avant, excepté les ſerre Files, juſqu' à ce qu'on ait pris la diſtance requiſe, qui doit être double de ce qu'elle étoit avant s'ouvrir.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="28" type="command">
                              <head>28.</head>
                              <p>Ouvrir les rangs en arriére de double di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, c'eſt faire que tous les rangs, horſmis les chefs de file, marchent en arriére, juſqu' à<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce qu'ils ayent pris leurs diſtances comme cy-deſſus.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="29" type="command">
                              <head>29.</head>
                              <p>Ouvrir les rangs en avant, &amp; en arriére à <pb n="32" facs="tcp:33947:24"/>double diſtance, c'eſt faire que tous les rangs, excepté les Chefs de demie file, marchent les uns en avant, &amp; les autres en arriére, juſqu' à ce qu'ils ayent pris leurs diſtances.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="30" type="command">
                              <head>30.</head>
                              <p>Ouvrir les files, c'eſt faire la diſtance plus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grande.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="31" type="command">
                              <head>31.</head>
                              <p>On fait ouvrir les files, en trois diverſes façon: ſçavoir, à droit, à gauche, &amp; à droit &amp; à gauche tout à la fois, à double diſtance.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="32" type="command">
                              <head>32.</head>
                              <p>Ouvrir les files à droite à double diſtance, c'eſt faire que toutes les files, à la reſerve de celle de main gauche, marche vers la main droit, juſqu' à ce qu'elles ayent pris leurs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, qui doivent être doubles de ce qu'elles étoient auparavant.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="33" type="command">
                              <head>33.</head>
                              <p>Ouvrir les files à gauche à double diſtance, c'eſt faire que toutes les files, à la réſerve de
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33947:25"/>la file de main droit, marchent vers la main gauche, juſqu' à ce qu'elles ayent pris leurs diſtances.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="34" type="command">
                              <head>34.</head>
                              <p>Ouvrir les files à droit, &amp; à gauche à dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſtance, c'eſt faire que toutes les files, excepté celle qui tient le milieu du Battaillon, marchent les unes vers la main droit, &amp; les autres vers la gauche, juſqu' à ce qu'elles ayent pris leurs diſtances.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="35" type="command">
                              <head>35.</head>
                              <p>Contremarche, c'eſt un mot compoſé, c'eſt à dire, marcher les uns contre les autres.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="36" type="command">
                              <head>36.</head>
                              <p>La Contremarche ſe fait en quatre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes maniéres; ſçavoir, par file à droit; par file à gauche, par rangs à droit, &amp; par rangs à gauche.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="37" type="command">
                              <pb n="36" facs="tcp:33947:26"/>
                              <head>37.</head>
                              <p>Faire la Contremarche par files à droit, c'eſt faire que les chefs de files, ſuivis de tout le Battaillon, s'avancent deux pas, aprés avoir fait demi tour à droit, ils marchent au contraire.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="38" type="command">
                              <head>38.</head>
                              <p>Faire la Contremarche par files à gauche c'eſt faire que les chefs des files, ſuivis des au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres comme deſſus, s'avancent deux pas, aprés avoir fait demi tour à gauche; qu'ils marchent auſſi, à l'encontre l'un de l'autre.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="39" type="command">
                              <head>39.</head>
                              <p>Faire la Contermarche par rangs à droit c'eſt aprés avoir fait faire à droit ou à gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che aux Battaillons, que ceux de la main droite, ou gauche facent ce qui à été dit, &amp; enſeigné au vingt troiſiéme Article des chefs de Files car alors, les Rangs ſont Files, &amp; iceux ſont faits Chefs de Files.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="40" type="command">
                              <pb n="38" facs="tcp:33947:27"/>
                              <head>40.</head>
                              <p>Faire la Contremarche par rangs à gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, c'eſt faire que le Battaillon face comme deſſus à ceux de la file de main droite ce qui a été enſeigné en l'Article dixhuitiéme pour les demies files.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="41" type="command">
                              <head>41.</head>
                              <p>Converſion eſt un mot tiré du Latin,
<hi>Converto;</hi> il prend ſon origine de la choſe à laquelle il ſert: car c'eſt comme qui diroit tourner tous enſemble, parce qu'on tourne, comme étans conjoints enſemble, tantôt d'un côté, tantôt de l'autre: &amp; on fait un quart, un demi tour, trois quarts, ou un tour tout entier de Converſion, à droite ou à gauche ſelon la volonté de celui qui com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="42" type="command">
                              <head>42.</head>
                              <p>Faire un quart de Converſion à droite, c'eſt faire que tout le Corps du Battaillon tourne vers la main droite, juſqu'à ce que le <pb n="40" facs="tcp:33947:28"/>Front du Battaillon prenne la place de l'Aîle droit,</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="43" type="command">
                              <head>43.</head>
                              <p>Faire la demi Converſion à droite c'eſt faire que tout le Corps du Battaillon tourne tout d'un temps vers la main droite, juſqu'à ce que le Front du Battaillon, prenne la place de la queüe.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="44" type="command">
                              <head>44.</head>
                              <p>Faire trois quarts de Converſion à droite, c'eſt faire que tout le Corps du Battaillon joint enſemble ſe tourne vers la main droite, juſqu'à ce que la face du Battaillon prenne le lieu que tenoit l'aîle gauche.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="45" type="command">
                              <head>45.</head>
                              <p>Faire la Converſion entiere, à droite, c'eſt faire que tout le Corps du Battaillon ſe tourne vers la main droite, juſqu'à ce que les chefs de files viennent reprendre la même place de laquelle ils ſont ſortis.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="46" type="command">
                              <pb n="42" facs="tcp:33947:29"/>
                              <head>46.</head>
                              <p>Faire un quart de tour, demitour, trois quarts de tour, ou le tour tout entier de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion à gauche, c'eſt faire que tout le Corps du Battaillon face vers la gauche ce qui à été fait cy-devant vers la droite.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="47" type="command">
                              <head>47.</head>
                              <p>Faire la Converſion par rangs à droite, c'eſt faire que tout les rangs du Battaillon façent enſemble un quart de Converſion vers la main droit, enſorte que tous enſemble fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent un ſeul rang, chaque rang étant conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu entre celui qui tient la main droite du même rang, &amp; celui qui tient la main droite du précédent.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="48" type="command">
                              <head>48.</head>
                              <p>Faire la Converſion par rangs à gauche, c'eſt faire que tous les rangs du Battaillon façent enſemble un quart de Converſion vers la main gauche, chaque rang étant contenu entre celui qui tient la main gauche de celui qui les précéde, faiſant ainſi comme deſſus, de tout les rangs un ſeul.</p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:33947:30"/>
                     <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Exercice général pour l'Infanterie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>L'Officier qui commande l'Exercice doit avoir toûjours loeil ſur ſes Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dats, les examinant depuis la tête juſqu'aux pieds, pour voir s'ils obſervent bien tous les temps, car la moindre faute eſt capable de faire manquer tout le Battaillon.</p>
                     <p>Les Sergens, &amp; les Caporaux doivent avoir ſoin, quand quelques nouveaux Soldats en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trent dans leurs Compagnies, de voir s'ils ſçavent bien l'Exercice: &amp; ſi ils ne le ſçavent pas, ils doivent le leur montrer en particulier, avant qu'ils le leur facent faire dans le Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taillon, parce qu'un ignorant broüille les au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, &amp; ſe broüille lui même auſſi. Les Sergens doivent toûjours mettre ſur les aîles, <pb n="46" facs="tcp:33947:31"/>&amp; à la tête du Battaillon ceux qu'ils con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noiſſent les plus capables, principalement à la file droite, parce qu'il faut que tous les Soldats ayent l'oeil ſur leur droite, ſans pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant tourner le Corps ni la tête d'aucun côté: c'eſt pourquoy on y met d'ordinaire les Caporaux, &amp; les Lanſpaſſades.</p>
                     <p>Il faut prendre garde, quand on fait un Commandement ſans s'expliquer, qué c'eſt toûjours en avant.</p>
                     <p>Quand on commande de marcher, ou de faire les quarts de Converſion, on doit toû<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jours partir du pied droit.</p>
                     <p>Les Sergens doivent toûjours être ſur les aîles du Battaillon, pour prendre garde ſi les Soldats font leur devoir, &amp; ſur tout, il faut faire obſerver un grand ſilence aux Soldats, car il eſt impoſſible qu'en faiſant du bruit ils puiſſent entendre le Commandement.</p>
                     <p>Aprés que toutes les Troupes ſont entrées dans le Champ de Battaille, &amp; qu'elles ont formé les Battaillons, on fait ouvrir les Files aux Battaillons, en faiſant le Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment qui ſuit.</p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:33947:32"/>
                     <div n="1" type="exercise">
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Prenez garde a vous pour ouvrir vos Files, que les Files de la droite ne bougent.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="exercise">
                        <head>2.</head>
                        <p>Le Commandement ſuſdit n'eſt que pour avertir les Soldats.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>A gauche, ouvrés vos files à un pas de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Marche.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut tourner un quart de tour vers la main gauche: la File de main droite ne doit point ſortir de ſa place.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Halte.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>A droit, c'eſt pourſe remettre comme on étoit.</p>
                        <p>On doit remarquer quand on fait à droit ou demi tour à droite qu'il faut ſe remettre par la gauche: &amp; ſi on fait à gauche, ou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour à gauche, il faut ſe remettre par la droite.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:33947:33"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Exercice du Mouſque, avec les temps qu'il faut obſerver pour bien appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre le maniment des Arms.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>PRenez garde à vous pour faire l'Exercice du Mouſquet.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div n="1" type="exercise">
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <p>Premierement, <hi>Portez bien vos Armes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Le Soldat doit obſerver que pour bien porter ſes Armes, il ne faut pas que ſon corps panche d'aucun côté: que ſes jambes ne ſoient ni trop ouvertes, ni trop ſerrées: Q'il ait ſon mouſquet ſur l'épaule gauche; le tenant ſur la croſſe de la main du même côté; que le coude ſoit bas. Il faut peſer ſur la croſſe, de maniére qu'elle ſoit prés de la cravate. La main droite doit être noncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamment étenduë le long de la cuiſſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:33947:34"/>
                        <head>2.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Portez la main droite ſur le Mouſquet:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut gliſſer tant ſoit peu le Mouſquet ſur l'épaule, &amp; le tourner, faiſant en ſorte que la platine ſoit en haut, les ongles deſſous, le coude levé à la hauteur de la main: en même temps qu'on gliſſe le Mouſquet, il faut porter la main droite au Mouſquet, au deſſous du Serpentin.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="exercise">
                        <head>3.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Haut le Mouſquet.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il fant peſer ſur le Mouſquet, le lever droit, le porter de la main droite en avant; vis à vis la cravate, &amp; faire un quart de tour vers la main droit, le bras bien étendu, &amp; la gauche nonchalamment poſé le long de la cuiſſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="exercise">
                        <head>4.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Joignez la main gauche au Mouſquet.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut porter la main gauche à la hauteur de la Ceinture, faiſant en ſorte que le Mouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet <pb n="54" facs="tcp:33947:35"/>ſe trouve appuyé ſur la main gauche. Il faut que les bras ſoient étendus en avant, en ſorte que le Mouſquet ſoit éloigné du Corps, de crainte qu'il n'arrive quelque acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent par le charbon de la méche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="exercise">
                        <head>5.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Prenez la méche.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut quitter la croſſe du Mouſquet, que l'on tient de la main droite, de laquelle on va prendre la méche, qui doit être poſée en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre le quatriéme, &amp; le petit doigt de la main gauche. Il eſt auſſi à obſerver, qu'il faut prendre la méche à deux doigts du char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon entre le poulce, &amp; le Second doigt. On doit porter la méche à la hauteur de l'épaule droite, le bras bien étendu, ayant le charbon en bas, &amp; au dedans de la main.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="exercise">
                        <head>6.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Soufflez la méche.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut porter la méche en la tournant prés de la bouche: il la faut ſouffler le plus fort qu'on pourra une ſeule fois: &amp; on doit aprés, <pb n="56" facs="tcp:33947:36"/>la rapporter à la hauteur de l'épaule, ou elle étoit, en attendant le Commandement qui ſuit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="exercise">
                        <head>7.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Mettez la méche ſur le Serpentin.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut porter la méche ſur le Serpentin &amp; prendre garde qu'elle ne ſoit ni trop longue ni trop courte du côte du charbon, car au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trement on courroit riſque que l'amorce ne prît pas feu: Il faut donc que vous portiez vôtre méche ſur le Serpentin, environ de la longueur d'un doigt &amp; demi du côte du Baſſinet.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="exercise">
                        <head>8.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Campaſſez la méche.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Ce Commandement n'eſt que pour ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver ce que je viens de vous expliquer, qui eſt de prendre garde ſi vôtre méche n'eſt pas trop longue, ou trop courte, trop cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bée, ou trop droite: c'eſt pourquoy on prend le Serpentin avec le poulce &amp; le ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond doigt de la main droite, &amp; on le baiſſe <pb n="58" facs="tcp:33947:37"/>ſur le baſſinet, pour voir ſi la méche eſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtement dans le milieu.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="exercise">
                        <head>9.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Mettez les deux doigts ſur le baſſinet.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut mettre le ſecond doigt, &amp; celui du milieu ſur le baſſinet le poulce doit être derriére le baſſinet, les deux bras étendus, le Mouſquet éloigné du corps, le bout du ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non toûjours haut.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="exercise">
                        <head>10.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Soufflez la méche.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut remarquer qu'il n'y a que les deux bras qui agiſſent, la tête, &amp; le corps doivent être toujours droits, on leve le Mouſquet en approchant contre la bouche la méche, qu'on ſouffle le plus fort qu'on peut, &amp; une foit ſeulement. Dans le même temps il faut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mettre le Mouſquet, &amp; les bras comme ils é<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toient avant ce Commandement.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="exercise">
                        <head>11.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ouvrez le Baſſinet.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:33947:38"/>
                        <p>Il faut laiſſer tourner le Mouſquet ſur la main gauche, en ſorte qu'il ſoit plat: ouvrir le baſſinet, &amp; dans le même temps qu'on l'ouvre, porter la main droite entre le baſſinet, &amp; la croſſe du Mouſquet, le poulce deſſus, &amp; les quatre doigts ſous la clef, de maniére qu'il ſoit prêt à tirer.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="exercise">
                        <head>12.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>En Joüe:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>A ce Commandement on preſente la Picque.</p>
                        <p>Il faut tourner le corps en avançant l'épaule droite à légal de l'autre, avancer les bras, &amp; le Mouſquet en avant, en ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochant la croſſe contre l'eſtomac, la tête droite, la veuë le long du canon, de ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niére qu'on puiſſe voir au bout du Mouſquet celui qu'on veut tirer: il faut avoir les coudes élevez &amp; d'égales hauteurs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="exercise">
                        <head>13.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Tirez.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il ne faut donner qu'un ſeul coup de clef,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33947:39"/>&amp; ſe tenir dans la même poſture juſqu'au Commandement qui ſuit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="14" type="exercise">
                        <head>14.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Retirez vos Armes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>A ce Commandement on fait haut la Picque.</p>
                        <p>Il faut un peu retirer le pied droit en ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riére, en ſorte que le corps ſoit droit, &amp; dans la même poſture qu'on étoit avant que de faire en jouë.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="exercise">
                        <head>15.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Prenez la Méche.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il la faur prendre de la même maniére que cy-devant: mais il faut obſerver que le charbon doit être haut, &amp; non en bas comme cy-devant, le bras bien étendu, tenant la méche vis à vis la Cravate.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="exercise">
                        <head>16.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez la méche en ſon lieu.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut la remettre entre le quatriéme &amp; le petit doigt, de la main gauche, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prendre <pb n="64" facs="tcp:33947:40"/>de la main droite le Mouſquet, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre la croſſe &amp; le baſſinet.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="exercise">
                        <head>17.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Soufflez ſur le Baſſinet.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut porter le Mouſquet en haut, en tournant le baſſinet du côte de la bouche, &amp; Souffler deſſus une ſeule fois, comme au ſouffle de la méche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="18" type="exercise">
                        <head>18.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Prenez le poulverin.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il ſe doit prendre avec la main droite, &amp; porter à la hauteur de la Cravate. Il faut que le bras ſoit bien étendu en avant.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="19" type="exercise">
                        <head>19.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Amorcez.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut baiſſer le bout du Mouſquet qu'on tient de la main gauche, en ſorte qu'il ſoit plat: on porte les poulverin ſur le baſſinet, dans le même temps qu'on amorce: on ne le doit pas retirer qu'on ne face le Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement qui fuit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="20" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:33947:41"/>
                        <head>20.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fermez le Baſſinet.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut laiſſer pendre le poulverin à la ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doliere, puis fermer le Baſſinet avec lé dedans de la paume de la main: enſuit on met la main comme auparavant, entre la croſſe &amp; le baſſinet, les bras bien étendus, &amp; le Mouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet éloigné du corps comme cy-deſſus.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="21" type="exercise">
                        <head>21.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Soufflez ſur le baſſinet.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut porter le Mouſquet en haut en tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant le baſſinet du côte de la bouche: ſouffler deſſius, une ſeule fois, comme au ſouffle de la mêche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="22" type="exercise">
                        <head>22.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Paſſez le Mouſquet du côté de l'épée.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut étendre les bras en portant le Mouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet en avant, paſſer la croſſe pardevant ſoy, en portant le pied droit en avant, comme ſi on vouloit faire un quart de tour vers la main gauche, ce faiſant il ſe trouvera du <pb n="68" facs="tcp:33947:42"/>côte de l'épeé: le canon doit être en bas le fuſt en haut, que l'on tient dans la paume de la main gauche, le bout du canon un peu levé.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="23" type="exercise">
                        <head>23.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Prenez la Charge.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>On la prend de la main droite, que l'on porte à la hauteur de la Cravate, le bras bien étendu.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="24" type="exercise">
                        <head>24.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ouvez la Charge avec les dents.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>On la porte auprés des dent, avec leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quelles on ouvre ladite charge: il faut la tenir toûjours dans la bouche, juſqu'au Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement quit ſuit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="25" type="exercise">
                        <head>25.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Mettez la poudre dans le canon.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut retirer la charge qu'on a entre les dents laquelle vous portez à la bouche du canon, dans lequel vous mettez la poudre, &amp; tenez la charge à la même place juſqu'au
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33947:43"/>temps qu'on face le Commandement qui ſuit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="26" type="exercise">
                        <head>26.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Tirez la bagette.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Elle ſe doit tirer en trois temps: il faut la prendre de la main droite: les ongles, en haut: quand elle eſt tout à fait tirée, il la faut porter en avant, le long du bras, la tenant à peu prés vers le milieu, le bras toûjours étendu: elle doit être poſée entre le poulce, &amp; le ſecond doit, le gros bout devant.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="27" type="exercise">
                        <head>27.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Haut la beguette.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut laiſſer tomber le gros bout de la baguette en bas, en ſorte qu'elle ſe trouve vis à vis de l'eſtomac &amp; un peu courbée.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="28" type="exercise">
                        <head>28.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Racourciſſez la baguette contre l'eſtomac.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut en ployant le bras, approcher le gros bout de la baguette contre l'éſtomac, la racou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cir à quatre doigs du bout, &amp; la tenir juſqu'au Commandement qui ſuit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="29" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="72" facs="tcp:33947:44"/>
                        <head>29.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Mettez la baguette dans le Canon.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut porter la baguelle au bout du Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, la mettre auſſi tôt dans le Canon: on la doit tenir dans la main, le poulce deſſus le petit bout de la baguette: il faut demeurer ainſi juſqu'au Commandement qui ſuit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="30" type="exercise">
                        <head>30.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Bourrez.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il fraut frapper trois coups de baguette ſur la poudre aſſez fort.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="31" type="exercise">
                        <head>31.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Retirez la baguette.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>A ce Commandement, il faut quitter la baguette, &amp; la reprendre, en tournant la main en dehors: puis la tirer le plus vîte qu'on pourra; &amp; étant tirée la porter plate à la hauteur de l'épaule, comme elle étoit au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paravant, horſmis qu'il faut que le gros bout ſoit du côte de l'épaule droite.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="32" type="exercise">
                        <head>32.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Haut la baguette.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il la faut tourner comme cy-deſſus, mais il ſaut que le petit bout ſoit en bas, &amp; le gros en haut, le bras bien étendu.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="33" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:33947:45"/>
                        <head>33.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Racourciſſez la baguette contre l'eſtomac.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut en ployant le bras, approcher le petit bout contre l'eſttomac, gliſſer la main le long de la baguette à quatre doigts du bout, &amp; la tenir ainſi juſqu'au Commandement qui ſuit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="34" type="exercise">
                        <head>34.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez la baguette en ſon lieu.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut la Porter à quatre doigts du bout, &amp; la mettre dans le même temps en ſa place, &amp; y étant miſe, on doit prendre le bout du Mouſquet de la main droite, à quatre doigts de l'embouchure.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="35" type="exercise">
                        <head>35.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Joignez la main droite au Mouſquet.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut repouſſer avec la main droite le bout du Mouſquet, en ſorte qu'il tourne ſur la gauche en tournant le poignet: dans le même temps porter la droite au deſſous du baſſinet.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="36" type="exercise">
                        <head>36.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Haut le Mouſquet.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut'dreſſer le Mouſquet, pour le porter de la main droite en avant: en faiſant un <pb n="74" facs="tcp:33947:46"/> 
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="76" facs="tcp:33947:47"/>quart de tour, vers la main droite, tenir la platine de ſon Mouſquet à la hauteur de la Cravate.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="37" type="exercise">
                        <head>37.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Mouſquet ſur l'épaule.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut rapporter le Mouſquet ſur l'épaule, où la main gauche doit prendre la place de la droite, laquelle doit aller nonchalam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment le long de la cuiſſe: rapportant le pied droit vers la main gauche: en faiſant un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quart de tour, on ſe remet de la maniére qu'on étoit cydevant au prémier Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Exercice de la Picque explique par temps.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div n="1" type="exercise">
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Picque en terre.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>IL la faut prendre de la main gauche à la hauteur de l'épaule, puis quitter le talon de la Picque, que l'on tient de la main droite, <pb n="78" facs="tcp:33947:48"/>pour la porter en haut au deſſus de la gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, en baiſſant la Picque, &amp; la main à la hauteur de la ceinture: dans le même temps la main doit être portée au deſſus, en ſorte qu'elle: ſe trouve à l'eſgal de l'oeil, quand elle ſera à terre: il faut qu'elle gliſſe le long du côte droit, ſans néanmoins y toucher, étant à terre, le talon de la Picque doit étre au côte de l'oreille du ſoulier, à laquelle il faut qu'il tienne en faiſant les quarts de Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, comme ſi elle étoit colée, le coude en bas, le bras le long de la Picque.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="exercise">
                        <head>2.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>A Droite.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire un quart de tour vers la main droite: on part du pied droit &amp; on tourne ſur le gauche: ce Commandement ſe fait quatre fois.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="exercise">
                        <head>3.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>A gauche.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>C'eſt la même choſe que cy-deſſus, au deuxiéme Commandement, qui eſt le quart du tour a droite, ſinon, qu'il faut faire à gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che; mais on tourne toûjours, ſur le même pied.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="81" facs="tcp:33947:49"/>
                        <head>4.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Demi tour à droite.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Pour faire ce Commandement, il faut tourner un demi tour à droit, de maniére qu'on ait le viſage où on avoit le dos.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="exercise">
                        <head>5.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>C'eſt la même choſe qu'au demi tour à droite, ſinon qu'il faut ſe remettre par gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="exercise">
                        <head>6.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Demi tour à gauche.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire comme cy-deſſus, au quatrié<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Commandement, ſinon qu'il faut tourner à gauche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="exercise">
                        <head>7.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire comme cy-deſſus, ſinon qu'il faut ſe remettre par droite.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="exercise">
                        <head>8.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Haut la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il la faut lever avec la main droite, de laquelle on la tient, &amp; en étendant le bras en haut, prendre la Picque de la main
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33947:50"/>gauche à la hauteur de la ceinture, puis, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver la Picque aſſez haut qu'on la puiſſe pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre de la main droite au talon, &amp; la joindre à l'épaule droite.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="exercise">
                        <head>9.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Preſentez la Picque en avant.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut porter la main gauche à la hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teur de l'épaule, prendre la Picque, &amp; la porter en avant, en étendant les bras: por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter un peu le pied en avant, puis le retirer en arriére avec la main droite, &amp; le talon de la Picque, laquelle on doit coucher le long du bras, paſſant entre le poulce, &amp; le ſecond doigt de la main gauche: le bras gauche doit être courbé ſur le ventre, &amp; le coudé en avant, le poignet faiſant face à la main droite.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="exercise">
                        <head>10.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>A droite, preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>En faiſant à droite, il faut lever la Picque, étendre les bras en avançant le pied droit, &amp; la Picque en avant, puis, faire un quart de tour vers la main droite, &amp; preſenter la
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33947:51"/>Picque comme cy-deſſus, au neuſié me Commandement: cétui-cy ſe fait quatre fois.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="exercise">
                        <head>11.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Demi tour à droite preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire comme cy deſſus, au dixiéme Commandement, ſinon, qu'au lieu de faire un quart de tour à droite, il faut faire le de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi tour tout entier, en ſorte qu'on ait le viſage où on avoit le dos.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="exercise">
                        <head>12.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>C'eſt la même choſe que cy deſſus, au onziéme Commandement, ſinon qu'il faut ſe remettre par gauche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="exercise">
                        <head>13.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>A gauche preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire comme cy-deſſus au dixié<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Commandement, ſinon, qu'au lieu d'a droite, il faut faire a gauche: il ſe fait qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre fois auſſi.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="14" type="exercise">
                        <head>14.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Demi tour à gauche, preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Ceſt la même choſe que cy-devant au de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33947:52"/>tour à droite, qui eſt l'onziéme Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, Sinon, qu'il faut tourner à gauche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="exercise">
                        <head>15.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut ſe remettre par droite: Il eſt à re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marquer que les Commandemens où il n'y a point d'explication pour le maniment de la Picque, il faut faire comme cy-deſſus, au neufiéme Commandement.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="exercise">
                        <head>16.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Picque de biais.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut, pour faire Picque de biais, l'ayant haute, porter la main gauche à la Picque à la hauteur de l'épaule, puis quitter le talon, porter le pied &amp; la main droite en arriére, en étendant le bras pour recevoir la Picque, laquel on doit rapporter ſur l'épaule droite, le talon doit être à un pied de terre.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="exercise">
                        <head>17.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Preſentez la Picque en avant.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut étendre le bras en portant la Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, &amp; le pied droit en arriére, puis, por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter la main gauche à la Picque, en ſuite, la faire tourner, ſur la main qui eſt la plus-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33947:53"/>du talon, en la quittant de la droite, pour la reprendre au talon, &amp; la preſenter: il faut qu'elle ſoit étenduë le long du bras gauche, poſée entre le poulce &amp; le ſecond doigt, ce qu'on appelle la fourche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="18" type="exercise">
                        <head>18.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>C'eſt la même choſe que cy-deſſus, au ſeiziéme Commandement: il n'y a qu'à rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter le pied &amp; la main en avant avec la Picque ſur l'épaule.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="19" type="exercise">
                        <head>19.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>A droite preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut preſenter la Picque comme il eſt dit cy-deſſus, au dixſeptiéme Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: il faut, aprés l'avoir portée en ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riére, la relever de la main droite, paſſer le talon devant ſoy, en tournant le corps &amp; le pied droit, prendre le talon avec la main droite, puis preſenter la Picque.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="20" type="exercise">
                        <head>20.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut repaſſer la Picque comme elle étoit avant que de la preſenter, c'eſt à dire, <pb n="90" facs="tcp:33947:54"/>qu'on doit porter le talon de la Picque en l'élevant, &amp; paſſer le pied droit à gauche, comme ſi on ne vouloit que faire un quart de tour à gauche, étendre le bras, &amp; la main pour recevoir la Picque: il faut faire encore un tour à gauche, pour la rapporter ſur l'é<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paule comme elle étoit au paravant.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="21" type="exercise">
                        <head>21.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Demi tour à droit preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut porter la Picque comme cy-deſſus, au dixſeptiéme Commandement: mais quand la Picque eſt en arriére, il faut faire le demi tour à droite en paſſant le talon de la Picque devant ſoy, puis la prendre de la main droite, &amp; la preſenter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="22" type="exercise">
                        <head>22.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire comme cy deſſus au demi tour à droite, ſinon qu'il faut ſe remettre par gauche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="23" type="exercise">
                        <head>23.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>A gauche preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire comme cy-deſſus, au dixneu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiéme Commandement, mais il faut, aprés <pb n="92" facs="tcp:33947:55"/>avoir porté la Picque en arriére, la rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter par deſſus la tête, en rapportant le pied droit comme ſion vouloit faire un quart de tour à gauche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="24" type="exercise">
                        <head>24.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Pour ſe remettre, il faut repaſſer la Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que pardeſſus la tête, en faiſant un quart de tour vers la main droite, le reſte comme cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſus, au dixſeptiéme Commandement.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="25" type="exercise">
                        <head>25.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Demi tour à gauche, preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire comme cy-deſſusau dixſeptié<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, &amp; au vingt troiſiéme Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens: toute la difference qu'il y a, c'eſt qu'il faut faire en cétui-cy le demi tour, au liou du quart de tour.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="26" type="exercise">
                        <head>26.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>C'eſt toute la même choſe que cy-deſſus, au vingt quatriéme Commandement, au lieu d'un quart de tour, il en faut faire un demi.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="27" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="94" facs="tcp:33947:56"/>
                        <head>27.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Picque demi traînante, le fer devant.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Pour faire ce Commandement, ayant la Picque de biais, il faut porter la main gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che à la Picque, que l'on tient de la main droite ſur l'épaule, puis en la levant il faut un peu lâcher le pied du même côte, en portant la Picque en arriére; puis la pouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer en arriére de la main gauche en tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant la Picque en avant, avec la droite, en ſorte quelle ſoit ſous le bras, &amp; le fer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, &amp; faire un quart de tour vers la main gauche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="28" type="exercise">
                        <head>28.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Preſentez le Picque en avant.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Pour faire ce Commendement, il faut avancer la Picque, le bras, &amp; le pied droit en avant, puis, prendre la Picque de la main gauche entre le corps, &amp; la main droite, de l'aquelle on quitte la Picque, pour la repren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre au talon, en la portant, avec le pied droit, en arriére, le bras gauche ployé ſur le ventre, la Picque entre la fourche de la main comme cy-devant, au neufiéme Commandement.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="29" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="96" facs="tcp:33947:57"/>
                        <head>29.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut avancer le pied droit, quitter le talon de la Picque, que l'on tient de la main droite, la porter en avant ſans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muer la gauche, puis prendre la Picque de la droite, la rapporter ſous le bras, le pied droit à l'eſgal du gauche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="30" type="exercise">
                        <head>30.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>A droite, preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut avancer la Picque, le bras &amp; le pied droit en avant, porter la main à la Picque, entre le côte droit, &amp; la main de laquelle on tient la Picque: puis, quitter la droite, pour la porter au talon, le pied droite en arriére: Il eſt à remarquer que la Picque étant comme ſi on avoit deſſein de la preſenter en avant, il faut qu, auſſi tôt qu, elle eſt dans cette poſture la lever auſſi, en la portant en avant, les bras bien étendus, le pied droit au côte du gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che: mais dans le même temps, il faut faire un quart de tour vers la main droite, &amp; y preſenter la Picque.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="31" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="98" facs="tcp:33947:58"/>
                        <head>31.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Pour ſe remettre, ayant preſenté la Picque a droite, il faut lever la Picque, étendre le bras, faire un quart de tour à gauche, lâcher le talon de la Picque en arriére que l'on tient de la main droite; puis avancer le pied, &amp; la main droite en avant, pour prendre la Picque, afin de la rapporter avec le bras, le pied comme ſi on vouloit faire un quart de tour vers la main gauche, de maniére qu'on ſe trouve en avant, la Picque ſous le bras droit, &amp; le pied à l'égal de l'autre.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="32" type="exercise">
                        <head>32.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Demi tour à droite preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il eſt à remarquer que ce Commandement eſt la même choſe qu'aux quart de tour à droit ſinon qu'au lieu d'un quart de tour, il faut faire un demi tour a droit; &amp; le reſte comme cy-deſſus, au vingt-neufiéme Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="33" type="exercise">
                        <head>33.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire comme cy-deſſus au trente
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33947:59"/>deuxiéme Commandement, ſinon qu'il faut ſe remettre par gauche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="34" type="exercise">
                        <head>34.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>A gauche, preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Ce Commandement eſt comme cy-deſſus au vingt neufiéme Commandement, au lieu de tourner à droite il faut tourner à gauche un quart de tour.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="35" type="exercise">
                        <head>35.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faur faire comme deſſus, au quart de tour à gauche, ſinon qu'il faut ſe remettre, par droite.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="36" type="exercise">
                        <head>36.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Demi tour à gauche, preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Ce Commandement eſt de même que le demi tour à droite: toute la différence qu'il y a, c'eſt qu'il faut faire à gauche, à cétui-cy, il faut voir cy-deſſus le vingt neufiéme Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="37" type="exercise">
                        <head>37.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire comme cy-deſſus au demitour à gauche, qui eſt le trente-ſixiéme Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, ſinon qu'il faut ſe remettre pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droite.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="38" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="102" facs="tcp:33947:60"/>
                        <head>38.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Picque dardante le fer devant.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Pour faire ce Commandement, ayant la Picque traînante le fer devant, il faut porter le bras, &amp; la Picque en arriére, faiſant un quart de tour à droite: puis, tourner la Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que en paſſant les doigts par deſſus, en ſorte qu'elle ſe trouve par deſſus la main, &amp; poſée entre le poulce, &amp; le ſecond doigt le ſer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant: il faut la rapporter en avant, faiſant un quart de tour vers la main gauche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="39" type="exercise">
                        <head>39.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Preſentez la Picque en avant.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Pour faire ce Commandement, il faut avancer le pied droit en avant, en paſſant la main droite, &amp; la Picque par deſſus la tête, prendre de la main gauche la Picque entre le talon, &amp; la main droite puis, la paſſer par devant ſoy en faiſant un quart de tour à droite, en portant la main droite au talon de la Picque, pour la preſenter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="40" type="exercise">
                        <head>40.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il ſaut pour ſe remettre, repaſſer la Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33947:61"/>que en avant, en avançant le pied droit, &amp; le corps dans le même temps: puis, quitter le talon qu'on tient de la main droit, reprendre la Picque au deſſus de la main gauche, &amp; la repaſſer par deſſus la tête pour ſe remettre en la même poſture qu'on étoit ayant preſenté la Picque en avant.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="41" type="exercise">
                        <head>41.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Demi tour à droite, preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il eſt à remarquer que ce Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſt bien different des autres, parce qu'il faut faire, au lieu d'un demi tour trois quarts de tour; Pour le bien exécu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: il faut porter la Picque en arriére, étendre le bras duquel on la tient, en por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant le pied droit du côte qu'on porte la Picque, étendant le bras en ſorte qu'elle ſe trouve entre le poulce, &amp; le ſecond doigt: puis tourner à droite en paſſant la Picque par deſſus la tête, tournant le ſecond doigt par deſſous la Picque, &amp; le poulce auſſi, &amp; les trois autres doigts, en ſuite étendre le bras, en avançant la Picque le long du bras droit, le fer auſſi à droite: l'oeil doit être <pb n="106" facs="tcp:33947:62"/>toûjours du côte du fer. Il faut porter la main gauche entre le talon de la Picque, &amp; la main droite, en levant la Picque, &amp; en la tournant pour la coucher ſur la gauche, la prendre de la droite au talon, puis la preſenter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="42" type="exercise">
                        <head>42.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut pour ſe remettre, aprés avoir fait à droite, faire un demi tour à gauche, en exécutant les temps qui ſuivent faire un quart de tour à droite en levant la Picque de la main gauche, quittant le talon que l'on tient de la droite, tourner la Picque, &amp; la coucher le long du bras droit, il faut qu'elle ſoit poſée dans la main, le ſecond doigt doit être deſſus les autres, ployer le poignet, tourner en dedans les ongles en haut puis, en faiſant à gauche, paſſer la Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que par deſſus la tête, étendre le bras en avançant le talon de la Picque du côte du pied droit, en ſorte qu'on puiſſe rapporter le pied &amp; la Picque tout d'un temps, en avant, en faiſant un quart de tour à gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, <pb n="108" facs="tcp:33947:63"/>de maniére que la Picque ſe trouve ſur l'épaule, le fer devant, entre le poulce, &amp; le ſecond doigt; c'eſt ce que nous ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellons fourchette.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="43" type="exercise">
                        <head>43.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>A gauche, preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut avancer le pied droit en avant, &amp; la main de laquelle on tient la Picque, en la paſſant par deſſus la tête, le bras bien étendu, &amp; la Picque en avant, porter la main gauche entre le talon, &amp; la main droite, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver la Picque devant ſoy, puis porter la main droite au talon, &amp; le pied droit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſi on vouloit faire un quart de tour à droite; il faut en ſuite, preſenter la Picque à gauche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="44" type="exercise">
                        <head>44.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire comme cy-deſſus, au quart de tour à gauche, qui eſt le quarante troi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiéme Commandement, ſinon qu'il faut ſe remettre par droite.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="45" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="110" facs="tcp:33947:64"/>
                        <head>45.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Demi tour à gauche preſentez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Le Commandement eſt de même que le quart de tour à gauche toute la diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence qu'il y a, c'eſt qu'il, faut faire le de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi tour à gauche.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="46" type="exercise">
                        <head>46.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire comme cy-deſſus au de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi tour à gauche, qui eſt le quarante cinquiéme commandement, ſinon qu'il faut ſe remettre par droite.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="47" type="exercise">
                        <head>47.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Haut la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut paſſer la Picque par deſſus la tête, en avançant le pied, la main droite, &amp; la Picque en avant: portant la main gauche entre le talon de la Picque, &amp; la main droite, puis la lever en haut, en portant la main droite au talon &amp; en tournant un quart de tour à droite: puis mettre la Picque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre l'épaule droite, &amp; le bras bien étendu, le gauche doit être non chalamment le long de la cuiſſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="48" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="112" facs="tcp:33947:65"/>
                        <head>48.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Preſentez la Picque à la Cavalerie.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut porter la main gauche à la Picque à la hauteur de l'épaule, puis la porter en avant, en avançant les deux bras, &amp; le pied droit, quittant le talon de la Picque: puis, porter la main droite au deſſus de la gauche, en baiſſant la Picque, en mettant le talon contre l'oreille du ſoûlier du pied gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che: il faut que le droit ſoit en avant, le corps panché ſur la cuiſſe droite, &amp; le fer de la Picque à la hauteur du poitrail du che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="49" type="exercise">
                        <head>49.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Tirez vos épées.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut porter par deffus la Picque, &amp; le bras gauche, la main droite, de laquelle on tire l'épée: puis il faut la croiſer ſur la Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que le bras droit étendu.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="50" type="exercise">
                        <head>50.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vos épées.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut un peu retirer le pied droit, &amp; la Picque, par deſſous laquelle il faut paſſer l'épée, &amp; le bras droit: puis, quitter la <pb n="114" facs="tcp:33947:66"/>Picque qu'on tient de la main gauche; la laiſſant poſée ſur le bras droit, pour prendre le fourreau de la main gauche, &amp; remettre l'épée avec plus de facilité; il faut en ſuite reprendre la Picque des deux mains à deux pieds de diſtance.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="51" type="exercise">
                        <head>51.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Haut la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut retirer le pied droit à l'égal de l'au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, redreſſer le corps en levant la Picque de la main droite, &amp; en la gliſſant dans la gauche, quitter le haut de la Picque, que l'on tient de la main droite, de laquelle on doit la prendre au talon, puis, la poſer contre l'épaule, le bras gauche contre la cuiſſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="52" type="exercise">
                        <head>52.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Preſentez la Picque en avant.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut faire comme cy-deſſus au neufiéme Commandement.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="53" type="exercise">
                        <head>53.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Marche.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut partir du pied droit, &amp; prendre garde de ne ſe pas avancer plus que-les au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres: il faut avoir toûjours l'oeil à droite, <pb n="116" facs="tcp:33947:67"/>&amp; à gauche, ſans pourtant tourner le corps d'aucun côte.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="54" type="exercise">
                        <head>54.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Halte.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut s'arrêter tout d'un coup, comme ſi on tenoit tous enſemble.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="55" type="exercise">
                        <head>55.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Alongez la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Pour bien alonger la Picque, il faut éten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre les bras avec force, &amp; néanmoins que le fer de la Picque ne branſle d'aucun côté, &amp; porte droit au corps de celui que vous pouſſez en alongeant la Picque: le talon doit être porté proche l'épaule gauche: il faut pouſſer la Picque, &amp; la retirer le plus promprement qu'on peut, afin que les coups ſoient plus fréquents.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="56" type="exercise">
                        <head>56.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Picque trainante le fer derriére.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut quitter le talon de la Picque, que l'on tient de la main droite, en faiſant demi tour à droite.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="57" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="118" facs="tcp:33947:68"/>
                        <head>57.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Marche.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut partir du pied droit, &amp; marcher juſqu'à tant qu'on diſe, <hi>Halte.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="58" type="exercise">
                        <head>58.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remettez vous.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut ſe remettre comme cy-devant, en faiſant un quart de tour vers la main gauche, &amp; en reprenant de la droite le talon de la Picque.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="59" type="exercise">
                        <head>59.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Haut la Picque.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Il faut avancer le pied droit â l'égal del'au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, en levant la Picque, en étendant les bras &amp; en portant la Picque en avant; puis, l'ap procher contre l'épaule droite, le bras gauche le long de la cuiſſe.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:33947:69"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Exercice pour de l'Infanterie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>APrés avoir mis le Régiment en bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taille, il faut faire obſerver le ſilence &amp; Commander aux Soldats de bien porter leurs armes.</p>
                     <div type="commands">
                        <head>On fait en ſuite, ouvrir les Files au Battaillon.</head>
                        <p>Prenez garde à vous pour ouvrir vos Files, que la File de la droite ne bouge.</p>
                        <p>A gauche, ouvrez vos Files à un pas de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
                        <p>Marche.</p>
                        <p>Halte.</p>
                        <p>A droite.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:33947:70"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Exercice du Mouſquet.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>PRenez garde à vous, pour faire l'Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cice du Mouſquet.</p>
                     <p>Portez la main droite au Mouſquet.</p>
                     <p>Haut le Mouſquet.</p>
                     <p>Joignez la main gauche au Mouſquet.</p>
                     <p>Prenez la méche.</p>
                     <p>Soufflez la méche.</p>
                     <p>Mettez la méche ſur le Serpentin.</p>
                     <p>Compaſſez la méche.</p>
                     <p>Mettez les deux doigts ſur le baſſinet.</p>
                     <p>Soufflez la méche.</p>
                     <p>Ouvrez le baſſinet.</p>
                     <p>En jouë: <hi>A ce Commandement, en preſente la Picque.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Tirez.</p>
                     <p>Retirez vos armes. <hi>A ce Commandement, on fait haut la Picque.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:33947:71"/>
                     <p>Prenez la méche.</p>
                     <p>Remettez la méche en ſon lieu.</p>
                     <p>Soufflez ſur le Baſſinet.</p>
                     <p>Prenez le poulverin.</p>
                     <p>Amorcez.</p>
                     <p>Fermez le baſſinet.</p>
                     <p>Soufflez ſur le baſſinet.</p>
                     <p>Paſſez le Mouſquet du côte de l'épée.</p>
                     <p>Prenez la charge.</p>
                     <p>Ouvrez la charge avec les dents.</p>
                     <p>Mettez la poudre dans le canon.</p>
                     <p>Tirez la baguette.</p>
                     <p>Haut la baguette.</p>
                     <p>Racourciſſez la baguette contre l'eſtomac.</p>
                     <p>Mettez la baguette dans le canon.</p>
                     <p>Bourrez.</p>
                     <p>Tirez la baguette.</p>
                     <p>Haut la baguette.</p>
                     <p>Raccourciſſez la baguette contre l'Eſtomac.</p>
                     <p>Remettez la baguette en ſon liea.</p>
                     <p>Joignez la main droit au Mouſquet.</p>
                     <p>Haut le Mouſquet.</p>
                     <p>Mouſquet ſur l'épaule.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:33947:72"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Exercice de la Picque.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>PRenez garde à vous Picquiers.</p>
                     <p>Picque en terre.</p>
                     <p>A droit, à droit, à droit, à droit.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à Droit.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, à gauche, à gauche, à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Haut la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Preſentez la Picque en avant.</p>
                     <p>A droit, à droit, à droit, à droit.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à droite.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, à gauche, à gauche, à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:33947:73"/>
                     <p>Haut la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Preſentez la Picque en avant.</p>
                     <p>A droite, à droite, à droite, à droite.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à droite.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, a gauche, à gauche, à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Haut la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Preſentez la Picque en avant.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A droite, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à droite, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à gauche, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Picque de biais.</p>
                     <p>Preſentez la Picque en avant.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A droit, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:33947:74"/>
                     <p>Demi tour à droite, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Haut la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Preſentez la Picque en avant.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Haut la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Picque demi-traînante le fer derriere.</p>
                     <p>Preſentez la Picque en avant.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A droite, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à droite, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à gauche, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Picque dardante, le fer devant.</p>
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:33947:75"/>
                     <p>Preſentez la Picque en avant.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A droit, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à droit, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à gauche, preſentez la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Haut la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Preſentez la Picque à la Cavalerie.</p>
                     <p>Tirez vos épées.</p>
                     <p>A droit, à droit, à droit, à droit.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à droite.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, à gauche, à gauche, à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vos épées.</p>
                     <p>Haut la Picque.</p>
                     <p>Preſentez la Picque en avant</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>Alongez la Picque.</p>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:33947:76"/>
                     <p>Picque traînante, le ferderriére.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Haut la Picque.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Exercice de tout le Battaillion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>PRenez garde à vous, tout le Battaillon, pour preſenter vos armes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mouſquetaires, apprêtez vous.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Les Picques ſe preſentent en même temps.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, à droit, à droit, à droit.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à droit.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, à gauche, à gauche, à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Prenez la méche.</p>
                     <p>Remettez la en ſon lieu.</p>
                     <p>Mouſquet ſur l'épaule.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>On fait haut la Picque.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:33947:77"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prenez garde à vous tout le Battaillon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, à droit, à droit, à droit.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à droite.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, à gauche, à gauché, à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rangs qui devez doubler, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Doublez vos rangs en avant.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Rangs, remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, doublez vos rangs en avant.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Rangs, remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rangs qui n'avez pas doublé, prenez garde a vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, doublez vos rangs en arriére.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Rangs remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, doublez vos rangs en arriére.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Rangs remettez vous.</p>
                     <pb n="138" facs="tcp:33947:78"/>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chefs de demies files prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, par chef de demies files, doublez vos rangs en avant.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par ſerre-files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, par chefs de demies files, doublez vos rangs en avant.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par ſerre files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Serre demies files, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, par ſerre demies-files, doubles vos rangs en arriére.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par chef de files, remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, par ſerre demie-files, doublez vos rangs en arriére.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>par chef de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Serre files, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="140" facs="tcp:33947:79"/>
                     <p>A droite par Serre file, doublez vos rangs à la tête.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par chef de demies-files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, par Serre file, doublez vos rangs à la tête.</p>
                     <p>marche.</p>
                     <p>Par chef de demies-files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chefs de files prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, par chefs de files doublez vos rangs à la queûe.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à droit, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à gauche, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par Serre demies files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, par chefs de files, doublez vos rangs à la queuë.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Demi Rangs, prenez garde à vous pour Serrer vos files.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par demis rangs, Serrez vos files.</p>
                     <pb n="142" facs="tcp:33947:80"/>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chefs demies files, prenez garde à vous, pour doubler vos rangs en avant ſur les aîles.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droite, &amp; à gauche par chefs de demies files doublez vos rangs en avant ſur les aîles.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par Serre files remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Serre demies file, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par ſerre demies files, doublez vos rangs en arriêre, ſur les aîles.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par chefs de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chefs de demies files, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droite, &amp; à gauche, par chefs de demies files, doublez vos rangs, en avant, &amp; en dedans.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Demis rangs prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droite, &amp; à gauche par demis rangs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prenez vos diſtances.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:33947:81"/>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Les files qui devez doubler, prenez garde d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, doublez vos files, Marche.</p>
                     <p>A droit, triplez vos files, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Files, remettez vous, Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Files, qui n'avez pas doublé, prenez garde d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A gauche, doublez vos files, Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, triplez vos files, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Triplez vos Files, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Files remettez vous, Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Demis rangs, prenez garde à vous, pour dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler vos files.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, par demis rangs, doubles vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Demis rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Demis rangs; qui n'avez pas doublé, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A gauche par demisrangs doublez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Demis rangs remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:33947:82"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Demis rangs, prenez garde à vous, pour double vos files par tête &amp; par queuë.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droite, par demis rangs, doublez vos files par tête, &amp; par queuë. Marche.</p>
                     <p>Demis rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Demis rangs qui n'avez pas doublé, prene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A gauche, par demis rangs, doublez vos files par tête, &amp; par queuë.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Demis rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Demis rangs, prenez garde à vous, pour doubler, vos files en dedans.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droite, par demis rangs, doublez vos files en dedans, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Demis rangs, remettez vos files, Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Demis rangs qui n'avez pas doublé, prenez gard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A gauche par demis rangs, doublez vos files en dedans.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Demis rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche,</p>
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:33947:83"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de rangs, prenez garde à vous, pour doubler vos files.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, par quarts de rangs, doublez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de rangs qui n'avez pas doublé prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A gauche, par quarts de rangs, doublez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de rangs des aîles, prenez garde à vous, pour doubler vos files ſur les quarts de rangs du milieu.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par quarts de rangs des aîles, doublez vos files ſur les quarts de rangs du milieu.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de rangs du milieu, prenez garde à
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:33947:84"/>vous, pour doubler vos files ſur les quarts de rangs des aîles.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par quarts de rangs du milieu, doublez vos files ſur les quarts de rangs des aîles.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de rangs, prenez garde à vous, pour doubler vos files par tête; &amp; par queuë.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droite par quarts de rangs, doublez vos files par tête, &amp; par queuë.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de rangs, qui n'avez pas doublé, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A gauche par quarts de rangs, doublez vos files par tête, &amp; par queuë.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de rangs de aîles, prenez garde à vous, pour doubler vos files ſur les quarts <pb n="152" facs="tcp:33947:85"/>de rangs du milieu, par tête, &amp; par queuë.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droite, &amp; à gauche, par quarts de rangs des ailes, doublez vos files ſur les quarts de rangs du milieu par tête, &amp; par queuë.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de rangs du milieu, prenez garde à vous, pour doubler vos files ſur les quarts de rangs, des aîles par tête, &amp; par queuë.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par quarts de rangs du milieu, doublez vos files ſur les quarts de rangs des aîles, par tête, &amp; par queuë.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de rangs, prenez garde à vous, pour dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler vos files en dedans.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit par quarts de rangs, doublez vos files en dedans.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de rangs, qui n'avez pas doublé, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="154" facs="tcp:33947:86"/>
                     <p>A gauche, par quarts de rangs, doublez vos files en dedans.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de rangs des aîles, prenez garde à vous, pour doubler vos files ſur les quarts de rangs du milieu en dedans.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par quarts de rangs des aîles, doublez vos files ſur les quarts du milieu en dedans.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de rangs remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de rangs du milieu, prenez garde à vous, pour doubler vos files, ſur les quarts de rangs des aîles en dedans.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit &amp; à gauche, par quarts de rangs du milieu, doublez vos files ſur les quarts de rangs des aîles.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de rangs remettez vous.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="156" facs="tcp:33947:87"/>
                     <head>CHAP. X. <hi>De la maniére qu'il faut faire la Contremarche.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>PRenez garde à vous tout le Battaillon pour faire la Contremarche.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit par rangs faites la Contremarche.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>A gauche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, par rangs, faites la Contremarche.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche.</p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par quarts de rangs, faites la Contremarche.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche.</p>
                     <p>A droit par files, faites la Contremarche.</p>
                     <p>Marche</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <pb n="158" facs="tcp:33947:88"/>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche.</p>
                     <p>A droit par Files, faites la contremarche.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à droit.</p>
                     <p>A gauche par files, faites la Contremarche.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>Demi tour à gauche.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>De la maniére qu'il faut faire les quarts de Converſion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>PRenez garde à vous tout le Battaillon, pour faire un quart de Converſion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, un quart de Converſion.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, un quart de Converſion.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="160" facs="tcp:33947:89"/>
                     <p>Repoſez vous ſur vos armes. <hi>Les Picquiers font Picques en terre.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Poſez vos armes à terre. <hi>Les Picquiers doi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent mettre Leurs Picques à terre entre les deux pieds, Il y à quelques endroits qui les mettent au côte droit: Je ne condamne point leur maniére, mais il faut toûjours chercher le plus facile &amp; le plus vîte.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Demi tour à droit, &amp; demi tour à gauche, rompez le Battaillon.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A vos armes.</p>
                     <p>Prenez vos armes.</p>
                     <p>Mouſquet ſur l'épaule. <hi>Les Picquiers font auſſi, haut la Picque.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Exercice par quarts de files.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ON met le Battaillon à huit de hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teur, &amp; on fait le Commandement fui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="162" facs="tcp:33947:90"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de files, prenez garde à vous, pour doubler vos rangs en avant.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, par quarts de files, doublez vos rangs en avant. Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, par quarts de files, doublez vos rangs en avant, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts des files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de files, prenez garde à vous, pour doubler vos rangs en arriére.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, par quarts de files, doublez vos rangs en arriére, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, par quarts de files, doublez vos rangs en arriére, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de files, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chefs de demi file, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit par chefs de demies files, doublez vos rangs en avant, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par ſerre file, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <pb n="164" facs="tcp:33947:91"/>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, par chef de demies files, doublez vos rangs en avant, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par ſerre file, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Serre file, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, par ſerre de demies files, doublez vos rangs en arriére, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par chefs de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, par ſerre de demies files, doublez vos rangs en arriére, Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par chefs de files, remettez vos rangs. Marche</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de files, de la tête, &amp; de la queuë, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, par quarts de files de la tête, &amp; de la queuë, doublez vos rangs en avant, &amp; en arriére, ſur les quarts des files du milieu.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, par quarts de files de la tête, &amp; de la queuë, doublez vos rangs en avant, &amp; en arriére, ſur les quarts de files du milieu.</p>
                     <pb n="166" facs="tcp:33947:92"/>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de files du milieu prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, par quarts de files du milieu, doublez vos rangs en avant, &amp; en arriére, ſur les quarts de files de la tête, &amp; de la queuë.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de files remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A gauche, par quarts de files du milieu, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blez vos rangs en avant, &amp; en arriére ſur les quarts de files de la tête, &amp; de la queuë,</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Demis rangs, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit &amp; à gauche; par demis rangs, ſerrez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prenez garde à vous, pour doubler vos rangs en avant ſur les aîles.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par quarts de files, doublez vos rangs en avant ſur les aîles.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <pb n="168" facs="tcp:33947:93"/>
                     <p>Quarts de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A droit &amp; à gauche par quarts de files, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blez vos rangs en arriére ſur les aîles.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A droit &amp; à gauche par quarts de rangs, doublez vos rangs en avant endedans.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par quarts de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche par quarts de files,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blez vos rangs en arriére, &amp; en dedans.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par quarts de rangs, remettez vos files.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chefs de demies files, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit &amp; à gauche, par chefs de demies files, doublez vos rangs en avant ſur les aîles. Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par ſerre files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Serres demies files, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="170" facs="tcp:33947:94"/>
                     <p>A droit &amp; à gauche, par ſerre demies, files, doublez vos rangs en arrriére ſúr les aîles. Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par ſerre files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Serres demies files, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit &amp; à gauche, par ſerre demies files, doublez vos rangs en arriére, en dedans, ſur les ailes.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par chefs de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chefs de demies files, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par chefs de demies files, doublez vos rangs en avant, en de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dans. Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par Serre files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Serre demies files, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par ſerre demies files, doublez vos rangs en arriére en dedans.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Par chefs de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <pb n="172" facs="tcp:33947:95"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de files de la tête, &amp; de la queuë, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par quarts de files de la tête &amp; de laqueuë, doublez vos rangs en avant, &amp; en arriére ſur les quarts de files du milieu ſur les aîles Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de file du milieu, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par quarts de files du milieu, doublez vos rangs en avant, &amp; en arriére, ſur les quarts de files de la tête &amp; de la queuë ſur les aîles. Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de files de la tête &amp; de la queuë, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par quarts de files de la tête &amp; de la queuë, doublez vos rangs en arriére, ſur les quarts de files du milieu en dedans. Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de files, remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarts de files du milieu, prenez garde à vous.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="174" facs="tcp:33947:96"/>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, par quarts de files du milieu, doublez vos rangs en avant, &amp; en arriére, ſur les quarts de files de la tête, &amp; de la queuë en dedans.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Quarts de files remettez vos rangs.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>A droit &amp; à gauche, par demis rangs repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nez vos diſtances.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prenez garde à vous Picquiers, pour fraiſer le Battaillon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit &amp; à gauche, par rangs entiers de Picques, fraiſez le Battaillon par tête &amp; par queuë.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prenez garde à vous, pour vous remettre.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A droit, &amp; à gauche, reprenez vos rangs.</p>
                     <pb n="176" facs="tcp:33947:97"/>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>A droite, &amp; à gauche.</p>
                     <p>Marche.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>Remettez vous.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>De la maniére qu'il ſe faut com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter dans toutes ſortes de Dé<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filés.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IL faut prendre garde dans les Défilés, que les Files ſoient toûjours non pair: &amp; lors qu'il ſe trouvera des files ſurnumé<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raires, on en formera des rangs à la queüe de la diviſion.</p>
                     <p>Obſervez lors que les diviſions défilent, que dans les endroits où on tourne par quart de Converſion, les rangs tournent à l'en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droit où le prémier rang aura tourné, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <pb n="178" facs="tcp:33947:98"/>garde de ſuivre le chef de file pas à pas.</p>
                     <p>Pour cét effet, les Sergens de la diviſion demeureront fermes à l'endroit où elle doit tourner, juſqu'à ce que les derniers rangs ayent paſſé, &amp; defilé,</p>
                     <p>Lors qu'on défile ſur un Pont devant les Ennemis, aprés que les hommes détâchez ont paſſé, il faut faire defiler le Battaillon par rangs, par le Centre: il faut faire les quarts de converſion, &amp; de demi conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>De la maniére qu'il faut tirer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LA meilleure maniére de tirer, eſt par rangs, lors qu'on veut faire ſon feu en ligne paralelle aux Ennemis.</p>
                     <p>Pour cét effet, pour tirer ſans embarras, il eſt bon de tirer de pied ferme, ſans faire <pb n="180" facs="tcp:33947:99"/>aucun mouvement, que celui de faire mettre les cinq prémiérs rangs genoux à terre; &amp; le ſixiéme eſt celui qui fait le prémier ſon feu: Le cinquiéme ſe relevant fait la même choſe, &amp; le reſte conſécutivement. Il faut que let rangs ſoient ſerrez à deux pas de diſtance, avant que l'eſcarmouche commence.</p>
                     <p>Quand on veut ſoûtenir un feu par dé<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachez, ſoit à un paſſage de riviere, chemin creux; ou en retraite, il faut détacher par files de la droite, &amp; de la gauche des Mouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetaires, qui ſeront inceſſamment conduits par des Officiers prépoſez pour cela.</p>
                     <p>Et revenans ainſi ſe remettre dans leurs poſtes, ils y ſeront conduits par les mêmes Officiers.</p>
                     <p>Quand on marche par diviſions pour ſe remettre en battaille en merchant, il faut pour plus grande facilité, premiérement doubler en trois corps, deux de Mouſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taires, &amp; celui de Picquiers: &amp; en ſuite, ſans perdre temps, joindre les trois corps en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble.</p>
                     <p>En faiſant ces mouvemens, il faut que la
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:33947:100"/>tête aille fort lentement, pour donner lieu à ceux, qui doublent, de joindre la tête ſans précipitation.</p>
                     <p>On peut auſſi, défiler en marchant de la même maniére, obſervant auſſi qu'il faut que la tête diligente le pas: &amp; que néanmoins le Battaillon marche inceſſamment d'un pas ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenti, ſans jamais faire Halte.</p>
                     <p>Quand le Régiment eſt en Battaille, &amp; qu'on veut faire défiler les Compagnies pour poſer les armes, ou retourner dans les quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, on fait marcher les deux aîles des Mouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetaires, &amp; les Picquiers reſtent derriére, faiſant qu'inceſſamment leſdites aîles des Mouſquetaires ſe ſerrant à droit &amp; à gauche, elle ſe joignent dans le terrain, qui ſera né<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaire pour donner lieu aux Picquiers, de ſe trouver châcun à la queuë de ſa Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnie: en ſuite de quoy châcune défile ſans perdre de temps, &amp; châque Officier en ſon poſte.</p>
                     <trailer>FIN.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33947:101"/>
                  <head>Table des Chapitres.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>LE Devoir du Major, <hi>Chap. 1. Page. 2</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>La maniére &amp; les termes d'un Battaillon,
<hi>Chap. 2 Page. 14</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Exercice général pour l'Infanterie, <hi>Chap.
3. Page. 44</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Exercice du Mouſquet expliqué par temps, <hi>Chap.
4. Page. 50</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Exercice de la Picque expliqué par temps, <hi>Chap.
5 Page. 76</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Exercice de l'Infanterie. <hi>Chap. 6. Page.
120</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Evercice du Mouſquet, <hi>Chap. 7. Page. 122</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Exercice de la Picque, <hi>Chap. 8. Page. 126</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Exercice de tout le Battaillon, <hi>Chap. 9. Page.
134</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De la maniére qu'il faut faire la Contremarche,
<hi>Chap. 10. Page. 156</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De la maniére qu'il faut faire les Quarts de Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, <hi>Chap. 11. Page. 158</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Exercice par quarts de files, <hi>Chap. 12. Page.
160</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Comme il faut ſe comporter dans toute forte de Défilez, <hi>Chap. 13. Page. 176</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De la maniére qu'il faut tirer, <hi>Chap. 14. Page.
178</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33947:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE PERFECT MAJOR: Shewing the eaſieſt way of handling ARMS, THE MILLITARY MOTIONS. WITH THE Manner how to enter into the Field, and to form a BATTALION.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>F. d' Morains,</hi> formerly an Officer in the
<hi>French</hi> Army's.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Licenſed</hi> April <hi>the</hi> 24th. 1686.</p>
                  <p>Ro. L'Eſtrange.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>B. Griffin</hi> for the Author,
1686.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33947:3"/>
                  <head>TO THE KING.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe natural and incomparable ſweetneſs of your MAJESTY, who receives the humble offerings of Strangers, as well as thoſe of your natural born Subjects, incourages me to take the liberty to conſecrate this Military Diſcourſe to your MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY, which treates briefly of the <pb facs="tcp:33947:4"/>moſt ſublime, moſt perillous, and moſt difficult Subject in the World: The skill of Noble Men, the practice of Men of Valour, and the Exerciſe of Princes and Kings. An Art by which to get Honour, we muſt be both Maſters and Scholars at once: For we muſt conquer in Learning, and learn in Conquering. This Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe contains what the moſt experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented of the Ancients do write upon that Subject: What I have heard ſay and ſeen practiced of late, by the braveſt Men that our Age affords, amongſt the moſt Warlike Nations of the World, which is a ſufficient Warrant for the Truth of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, but not ſo ſufficient as your MAJESTY's own experience, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <pb facs="tcp:33947:5"/>been your ſelf in perſon in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dangerous rencontres at the head of Armies, where your Royal Perſon was expoſed, as if you had been immortal, which is the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and the terrour of your MAJESTY's Enemies. Heaven grant that you may ſo excel in it, that the moſt generous Warriers may tremble at your Name, and ſeek for no other examples in Hiſtories, than thoſe of your great exploits. But Sir, if I was able to expreſs my ſelf upon this ſubject, inſtead of an Epiſtle, I ſhould make a Panegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick: But I want expreſſions, and I moſt humbly beg your MAJESTY's pardon, for the liberty I take to offer you this Diſcourſe, and to give me <pb facs="tcp:33947:6"/>leave to be ſilent wherein I cannot expreſs my ſelf: There is often much art in being ſilent, and ſilence was among the Ancients a great myſtery. And therefore I ſhall ſay no more, but only beg your MAJESTY's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and the favour to give me leave to make bold to ſubſcribe my ſelf, with the deepeſt reſpect,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>YOUR MAJESTIES, Moſt Humble, moſt Obedient, and moſt faithful Servant F. De MORAINS.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33947:7"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Courteous Reader;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Do not queſtion, but many envious people will blame me of temerity to have been ſo bold to dedicate this Diſcourſe to ſo great a Monarch: But if they reflect upon the Subject of this Book, and the neceſſity there is for the preſervation of a Kingdom, that the King's Forces may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their duty; they may in a manner approve the Zeal, which hath cauſed me to give it to the Publick, ſeeing my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is only to teach with an eaſie way the Handling of Arms, the Military moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with the manner how to enter into <pb facs="tcp:33947:8"/>the Field, Form a Battalion, to fire Retreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in the keeping of a Paſs, or a Hollow way, and in Defils. I give, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, this inſtruction of the manner of fighting now, as I have ſeen it, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed it my ſelf in the laſt Compagnes, which I offer very heartily to the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who always make it their chiefeſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to fight for their King, and for the glory of their Country, for both which they are obliged to ſpend their blood. If thoſe that will follow this glorious profeſſion can learn any thing in it, I ſhall think my ſelf the happieſt man in the World to ſee that my labour hath not been in vain. Farewell.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="English" type="version">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33947:9"/>
                  <head>THE PERFECT MAJOR: Shewing The eaſieſt way of Handling Arms, the Military motions' with the manner how to enter into the Field, and to form a Battalion.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I. The Major's Duty.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="duty">
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <p>THe Major is to take the Colonel's Company with his Adjutant, or <hi>Ayde Major,</hi> or him that officiates in his place, which is to lead into the field, after having view'd it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="duty">
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33947:10"/>
                        <head>2.</head>
                        <p>The Major is to receive the Musketeers, to make, and order the Front of the Battalion.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="duty">
                        <head>3.</head>
                        <p>The Adjutant is to be at the head of the Pikemen, which he ſhall order after the ſame manner behind the Musketeers, at twenty paces diſtance, if there be ground e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="duty">
                        <head>4.</head>
                        <p>The Major, or Adjutant, is to obſerve that the diſtance of the Files, when they do not exerciſe, is to be of half a pace: but when they are to exerciſe, they are to open at a pace diſtance.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="duty">
                        <head>5.</head>
                        <p>No Company ought to go into the Field but in it's proper Rank, or Order, and the Files are to be ſix deep.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="duty">
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:33947:11"/>
                        <head>6.</head>
                        <p>The Captains, or Officers are to lead their Companies with their Pikes in their hands. The Lieutenants are to be at the Rear of the Pikes, but when there is no Enſign, they muſt place themſelves at the head of the Pikes, when the Battalion is to be formed.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="duty">
                        <head>7.</head>
                        <p>The Companies entring the field, ſhall File off, and march upon the left Wing of the Pikes: but before, they are to leave their Pikes in the Field, and the Musketeers ſhall follow their march, until they joyn the Front of Musketeers.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="duty">
                        <head>8.</head>
                        <p>As ſoon as the laſt Company ſhall have joyned the Battalion, the Adjutant muſt make the Pikes file off by four at a breaſt, to go and joyn the Battalion upon the ſame Front <pb n="9" facs="tcp:33947:12"/>of the Musketeers upon the left Wing, and immediately, without loſing time, as ſoon as the laſt quarter Rank is come up, he muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the half Rank of the left of Musketeers to turn to the left, and the Pikes to the right, giving the word of Command, <hi>March.</hi> The Pikes and Musketeers ſhall keep the ſame ground, after which the Command muſt be, <hi>Return as you were.</hi> In this motion, there muſt be always a Serjeant upon the Wing of each rank, to prevent their falſe march.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="duty">
                        <head>9.</head>
                        <p>No Officer ought to leave the head of his Company, nor his Pike; till the Battalion is formed</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="duty">
                        <head>10.</head>
                        <p>As ſoon as a Battalion is formed the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Lieutenant muſt ſtay at the Rear of the right Wing of Musketeers, and the youngeſt Lieutenant at the Rear of the left Wing, an Enſign at the Rear of Pikes, with one half of the Serjeants, to prevent the <pb n="11" facs="tcp:33947:13"/>Soldiers from breaking, and quitting their Ranks.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="duty">
                        <head>11.</head>
                        <p>When the Major gives the word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, the Officers and Serjeants muſt command the Soldiers to keep ſilence, and no other, but the Major, ought to give the word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, except he that commands the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="duty">
                        <head>12.</head>
                        <p>The Captains, and Officers ſhall in the execution of the Motions, follow the Major's orders.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="duty">
                        <head>13.</head>
                        <p>The Drums are to be upon the Wings.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="14" type="duty">
                        <head>14.</head>
                        <p>It is requiſite that the Officers take care that the Soldiers do not neglect any thing concerning their Duty, as to keep well their Ranks, to carry their Arms well, and <pb n="13" facs="tcp:33947:14"/>to obſerve their diſtance, not only in the Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, but in the leaſt things; as in their Marches into the Field, Towns, or Villages, or when they ſtand Centry, for we often ſee Soldiers carry their Arms ſometimes upon one ſhoulder, and ſometimes upon another, and ſometimes under their Arms, which ought not to be ſuffer'd without cauſe, for whoever neglects ſmall things, in time will alſo neglect greater things, for neglect will turn into an habit: and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the under Officers ought to view their Soldiers Arms, to ſee if they are fixed, and in good order: and in caſe they be not ſo, after they have had warning of it, they muſt be got mended, and cleanſed, at their own coſt and charge, which they might do themſelves, if they were vigilant, which is the mark of a good Soldier. The Captains ought not altogether to truſt to their infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Officers: they ought, from time to time to take a review of their Companies, and at the ſame time to view their Arms; and in caſe they don't find them, as they ought to be, after they have commanded the Serjeants to have <pb n="15" facs="tcp:33947:15"/>a care of it, they muſt get them to be mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the charge of all the under Officers. They ſhall no ſooner have done it once, but that every one ſhall mind his Duty, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his poſt: For there muſt be ſome ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination in an Army.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. II. The manner how to Form a Battalion, and the terms which are to be uſed, with an eaſie method to learn the Military motions.</head>
                     <div n="forming a battalion" type="commands">
                        <head>In the firſt Place.</head>
                        <p>THe terms of a ſquare Battalion of Men.</p>
                        <p>The Battalion is made up of a File Leader, and a Bringer up, of a half File Leader, and of a Bringer up of a half File, of a right hand File, and of a left hand File.</p>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:33947:16"/>
                        <p>The fore part of the Battalion is called the Head, or the Front.</p>
                        <p>The hinder part is called the Rear.</p>
                        <div n="commands" type="explanation">
                           <head>The Explication of it, The manner how to form a Battalion, and the terms which are to be uſed.</head>
                           <div n="1" type="command">
                              <head>1.</head>
                              <p>The firſt File of a Battalion is that which is on the right hand of the Battalion, upon which all the reſt are to order themſelves.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="2" type="command">
                              <head>2.</head>
                              <p>A File is ſo many Men directly behind one another, all in a direct line, ſo that no man leaneth neither to the right, nor to the left.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="3" type="command">
                              <head>3.</head>
                              <p>To keep a ſtreight line, every Souldier in his File ſhall look his File-leader on the right hand, and on the left, and ſhall bend his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of neither ſide.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="4" type="command">
                              <pb n="19" facs="tcp:33947:17"/>
                              <head>4.</head>
                              <p>To even the Ranks, is to poſt the Men of every Rank in a direct line, ſide by ſide, and all of a Front, ſo that none be too much for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, nor too backward.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="5" type="command">
                              <head>5.</head>
                              <p>To even the Ranks, the Men of each Rank ſhall look before, and behind their right hand Man, without leaving their poſt, or as we ſhall ſhew hereafter, they ſhall turn to the right, or to the left, afterwards they ſhall poſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as it is order'd in the third Article.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="6" type="command">
                              <head>6.</head>
                              <p>A Battalion is to be drawn up ſix deep, when it is to fight: But when you exerciſe more carefully, you muſt put eight men to a File, that you may have quarter Files.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="7" type="command">
                              <pb n="21" facs="tcp:33947:18"/>
                              <head>7</head>
                              <p>The depth of the Battalion is divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to quarter Files; one is called the Front quarter File, and the other the Rear quarter File, or the out quarter File; and the other the Center quarter File.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="8" type="command">
                              <head>8.</head>
                              <p>When a Souldier turns, it muſt always be upon the ſame foot, which is commonly the left, to obſerve the diſtances, and when he changes place, he muſt always begin to ſtep with the right foot foremoſt.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="9" type="command">
                              <head>9.</head>
                              <p>If a Souldier will march backward, he muſt first turn to the right about.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="10" type="command">
                              <head>10.</head>
                              <p>To the right, is to turn a quarter turn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the right hand, and then to ſtand.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="11" type="command">
                              <head>11.</head>
                              <p>To the left, is to turn a quarter turn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the left hand.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="12" type="command">
                              <pb n="23" facs="tcp:33947:19"/>
                              <head>12.</head>
                              <p>To the right about, is to turn half a turn to the right hand, ſo that the man that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind you, may then be before.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="13" type="command">
                              <head>13.</head>
                              <p>To the left about, is to turn half a turn to the left hand, and to ſtand as above.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="14" type="command">
                              <head>14.</head>
                              <p>It is to obſerved that when the word of Command is given without further explication, it is to be always understood to be forward.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="15" type="command">
                              <head>15.</head>
                              <p>When the word of Command is to the Right, or to the Right about, it muſt be afterwards to the left, as you were: and if the word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is to the left, or to the left about, it muſt be afterwards to the right as you were, and you muſt take care to keep your Ranks even, and your Files ſtreight.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="16" type="command">
                              <pb n="25" facs="tcp:33947:20"/>
                              <head>16.</head>
                              <p>To double your Ranks to the right, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Rank muſt come up to the firſt, the fourth to the third, the ſixth to the fifth, and ſo in order come up upon the right hand of the Men that are before you, and ſhall be as before; only two Ranks ſhall make but one.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="17" type="command">
                              <head>17.</head>
                              <p>To double your Ranks upon the left, you muſt do as before, the ſecond Rank muſt come up to the firſt: but inſtead of coming up upon the right, you muſt come up upon the left.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="18" type="command">
                              <head>18.</head>
                              <p>To double your Ranks upon the right, by half Files; the half Files muſt march forwards to the Front, and paſs between the Bringers-up of half files, and every half file Leader muſt joyn upon the right.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="19" type="command">
                              <pb n="27" facs="tcp:33947:21"/>
                              <head>19.</head>
                              <p>To double your Ranks upon the left by half Files, you muſt march forward to the Front, and follow as before, taking the left hand of every half file Leader of them, who are to follow.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="20" type="command">
                              <head>20.</head>
                              <p>As you were, is to take the ſame poſt you had before.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="21" type="command">
                              <head>21.</head>
                              <p>Having doubled your Ranks ſingle, or by half Files upon the right, you muſt, quitting their Ranks, turn to the right about, and having taken your poſt to your first diſtance, you muſt turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the right about, and having doubled upon the left ſingle, or by half Files, you muſt, quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Ranks, turn to the right about; and having taken your diſtance, turn to the left about; and thus every man ſhall find himſelf behind him, who did march before him.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="22" type="command">
                              <pb n="29" facs="tcp:33947:22"/>
                              <head>22.</head>
                              <p>To double your Files to the right, is when the ſecond File of the right joyns to the firſt, and of two makes but one: and likewiſe the fourth to the third, the ſixth to the fifth, and ſo of the reſt by order, as many Files as there is.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="23" type="command">
                              <head>23.</head>
                              <p>To double your Files to the left, is when the ſecond File of the left joyns to the firſt, the fourth to the third, the ſixth to the fifth, in the ſame order as above.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="24" type="command">
                              <head>24.</head>
                              <p>To open your Ranks, is to make the diſtance of the Ranks wider.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="25" type="command">
                              <head>25.</head>
                              <p>To cloſe your Ranks, is to make the diſtance of the Ranks leſs.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="26" type="command">
                              <pb n="31" facs="tcp:33947:23"/>
                              <head>26.</head>
                              <p>The Ranks may be open three ſeveral ways; to the Front, to the Rear, and to the Front and and Rear, all at once, and often at double di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="27" type="command">
                              <head>27.</head>
                              <p>To open your Ranks to the Front at double diſtance, is when all the Ranks do advance for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, except the Bringers-up, till they have taken a requiſite diſtance, which ought to be double, of what it was before you opened your Ranks.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="28" type="command">
                              <head>28.</head>
                              <p>To open your Ranks to the Rear, at double distance, is when all the Ranks, except the file Leaders, do march backward, till they have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their diſtances as above.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="29" type="command">
                              <head>29.</head>
                              <p>To open the Ranks to the Front, and to the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33947:24"/>at double diſtance, is when all the Ranks, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the half-file Leaders, do march, ſome forward; and the other backward, till they have taken their diſtance.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="30" type="command">
                              <head>30.</head>
                              <p>To open your Files, is to make the diſtance wider.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="31" type="command">
                              <head>31.</head>
                              <p>You open your files three ſeveral ways, to the right, and to the left, and to the right and left at once at double diſtance.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="32" type="command">
                              <head>32.</head>
                              <p>To open your Files to the right at double diſtance, is when all the Files, except the left hand File, do march towards the right, till they have taken their diſtance, which ought to be double of what it was before.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="33" type="command">
                              <head>33.</head>
                              <p>To open your Files to the left at double di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, is when all the Files, except the right <pb n="35" facs="tcp:33947:25"/>hand File, do march towards the left hand, till they have taken their diſtance.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="34" type="command">
                              <head>34.</head>
                              <p>To open your Files to the right and left at double diſtance, is when all the Files, except that which is in the Center of the Battalion, march ſome to the right, and the others to the left, till they have taken their diſtance.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="35" type="command">
                              <head>35.</head>
                              <p>Countermarch, is a compound word, that is to ſay, to march one againſt another, to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change ground.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="36" type="command">
                              <head>36.</head>
                              <p>The Countermarch is done four ſeveral ways, that is to ſay, by Files to the right, by Files to the left, by Ranks to the right, and by Ranks to the left.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="37" type="command">
                              <pb n="37" facs="tcp:33947:26"/>
                              <head>37.</head>
                              <p>The Countermarch by Files to the right, is when the File Leaders, followed by the whole Battalion, do advance two paces, and after they have faced to the right about, do march, and interchange ground.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="38" type="command">
                              <head>38.</head>
                              <p>The Countermarch by Files to the left, is when the File Leaders, followed as above, do advance two paces, and after they have faced to the left about, do march and interchange ground.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="39" type="command">
                              <head>39.</head>
                              <p>The Countermarch by Ranks to the right, is when the Battalions have faced to the right or left, thoſe of the right, or left do obſerve what hath been ſaid, and ſhewed in the three and twentieth Article of the File Leaders, for then the Ranks are Files, and they become File Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="40" type="command">
                              <pb n="39" facs="tcp:33947:27"/>
                              <head>40.</head>
                              <p>The Countermarch by Ranks to the left, is when the Battalion doth as above, in the right hand Files what hath been ſhewed in the eighteenth Article of the half Files.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="41" type="command">
                              <head>41.</head>
                              <p>Converſion is a word taken from the Latin
<hi>Converto:</hi> it hath it's ſignification from the thing to which it is proper: for it is as if one ſhould ſay, to wheel all together, for the men muſt wheel as if they were all linkt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſometimes one way, ſometimes another: there is a quarter turn, a half turn, three quarters turn, and a whole turn of Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or wheeling to the right and left, as the Commander pleaſeth.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="42" type="command">
                              <head>42.</head>
                              <p>To make a quarter turn of Converſion, or to wheel to the right, is when the whole Body of the Battalion wheels all together upon the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33947:28"/>right, till the Front of the Battalion takes the place of the right Flank.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="43" type="command">
                              <head>43.</head>
                              <p>To make half a turn of Converſion, or to wheel to the right about, is when the whole body of the Battalion wheels all together upon the right, till the Front of the Battalion takes the place of the Rear.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="44" type="command">
                              <head>44.</head>
                              <p>To make three quarters of Converſion, or to wheel to the right, when the whole body of the Battaillon joyned together, wheels upon the right, till the Front of the Battalion takes the place of the left Wing.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="45" type="command">
                              <head>45.</head>
                              <p>To make the whole Converſion, or to wheel to the right, is when the whole body of the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion wheels upon the right hand, till the File Leaders come to the ſame posts they have quitted.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="46" type="command">
                              <pb n="43" facs="tcp:33947:29"/>
                              <head>46.</head>
                              <p>To make a quarter turn, half a turn, three quarter turn, and the whole turn of Converſion, or wheeling to the left, is when the whole body of the Battalion wheels upon the left, as they have done above upon the right.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="47" type="command">
                              <head>47.</head>
                              <p>To make the Converſion, or wheeling by Ranks to the right, is when all the Ranks of the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion make all together a quarter turn of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, or wheel upon the right, ſo that all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make but one Rank, every Rank being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained between that Rank, which hath the right hand of the ſame Rank, and that which hath the right hand of the foregoing Rank.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="48" type="command">
                              <head>48.</head>
                              <p>To make the Converſion, or wheeling by Ranks to the left, is when all the Ranks of the Battalion make all together a quarter turn of Converſion, or wheel upon the left, every Rank being contained between that Rank, which hath the left of the foregoing Rank, making as above, of all the Ranks, but one.</p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:33947:30"/>
                     <head>CHAP. III. The general Exerciſe of the Foot.</head>
                     <p>THe Officer, who commands the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, ought to have always his eyes upon his Soldiers, obſerving them from the head to the foot, to ſee if they obſerve well all the motions; for the leaſt ill motion is enough to put the whole Battalion in diſorder.</p>
                     <p>The Serjeants, and Corporals ought to have a care when ſome young Soldiers come into their Companies, to try if they know how to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe well; if they do not know it, they muſt ſhew it them in private, before they take them in the Battalion to exerciſe, becauſe an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Soldier diſorders and confounds all the reſt as well as himſelf. The Serjeants ought always to place upon the Wings; and at the Front of the <pb n="47" facs="tcp:33947:31"/>Battalion, thoſe men they know to be the moſt capable: and eſpecially, in the right File: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all the Soldiers are to have an eye upon their right hand man, without turning the body, or the head of any ſide: and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the Corporals, and the Lanſpaſſades are commonly poſted there.</p>
                     <p>You muſt take care, that when the word of Command is given without explication, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways underſtood to be to the Front.</p>
                     <p>When the word of Command is to march or to wheel, you muſt alwaies ſtep the right foot forward.</p>
                     <p>The Serjeants muſt always be upon the Wings of the Battalion to have a care that the Soldiers do their duty, and above all that they obſerve the ſilence, for if they make a noiſe, it is impoſſible they ſhould hear the word of Command.</p>
                     <p>After all the forces are come up into the Field, and have formed the Battalions, the ſaid Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talions muſt open their Files at the following word of Command</p>
                     <div n="1" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:33947:32"/>
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Take heed to open your Files. The right hand Files, ſtand.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="exercise">
                        <head>2.</head>
                        <p>The foregoing word of Command is only to give notice to the Soldiers.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>To the left, open your Files at a pace di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>March.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You must turn a quarter turn towards the left hand, the right hand Files muſt ſtand, and keep their ground.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Halt.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To the right, it is to return as you were.</p>
                        <p>You muſt obſerve, when you turn to the right, or to the right about, you must return as you were by the left. And if you turn to the left, or to the left about, you muſt return as you were by the right.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:33947:33"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IV. The Exerciſe of the Musket, with the motions that are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, to learn perfectly the handling of Arms.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>SOldiers, take heed to exerciſe the Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div n="1" type="exercise">
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <p>In the firſt place, <hi>carry your Arms well.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Soldier is to obſerve that for to carry his Arms well, his Body muſt lean of neither ſide: his Legs muſt neither be too open, nor too cloſe, having his Musket upon his left Shoulder, holding the but end of it with the left hand, his elbow must be low, he muſt graſp it hard, ſo that the but-end be near his Cravat, and his right hand is to hang down careleſly along his thigh.</p>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:33947:34"/>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="exercise">
                        <head>2.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lay your right hand on your Musket.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt ſlip your Musket a little upon your Shoulder, and turn it with the Lock uppermoſt, your Nails under your Elbow, even with your hands; at the ſame time that you ſlip your Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, you muſt joyn your right hand to your Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, under the Cock of your Musket.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="exercise">
                        <head>3.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Poize your Musket.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt graſp your Musket hard, and carry it off ſtreight with your right hand forward, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven before your Cravat, and turn to the right, extend your right arm, and let the left hand hang down careleſly along your thigh.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="exercise">
                        <head>4.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Joyn your left hand to your Musket: or reſt your Musket.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt bring your left hand to the height of your waſte, ſo that your Musket may reſt <pb n="55" facs="tcp:33947:35"/>upon your left hand, your arm muſt be extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forward, ſo that your Musket be from your body, for fear any accident ſhould happen oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by the Cole of your Macth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="exercise">
                        <head>5.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Handle your Match.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You must quit the but-end of your Musket which you held with the right hand, with which hand you muſt take your Match, which muſt be between the fourth and little Finger of your left hand: you must alſo obſerve that you muſt take your Match with your Thumb and firſt Finger, two inches from the Cole: you must carry your Match even to your right Shoulder, your right arm being well extended, holding the Cole downwards and in the palm of your hand.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="exercise">
                        <head>6.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Blow your Match.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt bring up your Match, turning your hand near your mouth, and having blown a quick ſtrong blaſt, once only, caſt out your arm <pb n="57" facs="tcp:33947:36"/>again, even to your Shoulder, as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, expecting the following word of Command.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="exercise">
                        <head>7.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cock your Match.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt bring your Match to the Cock, and take heed that it neither be too long, nor too ſhort towards the Cole: for if it were ſo, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps your piece would not go off: you muſt therefore bring your Match to the Cock, the length of about an inch towards the pan.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="exercise">
                        <head>8.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Try your Match.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This word of Command is but to make you obſerve that which I have explained juſt now, which is to take heed that your Match be neither too long, nor too ſhort, neither too much bent, nor too ſtreight; therefore you muſt take your Cock with your Thumb, and the ſecond Finger of the right hand, then bring <pb n="59" facs="tcp:33947:37"/>it to the pan, to ſee whether it falls juſt in the middle.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="exercise">
                        <head>9.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Guard your Pan.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt lay your ſecond or middle Finger upon the Pan, your Thumb behind it, both your Arms extended, your Musket from your Body, and the muzzel of your Musket always up.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="exercise">
                        <head>10.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Blow your Match.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt obſerve, that both your Arms on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly move: you muſt alwayes keep your head and body ſtreight, without stooping, raiſe your Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, bringing your Match to your Mouth, blow a ſtrong blaſt, and once only at one motion; then return your Musket and your Arms as they were before the word of Command.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="exercise">
                        <head>11.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Open your Pan.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:33947:38"/>
                        <p>You muſt ballance you Musket upon the left hand when you open the Pan; at the ſame time that you open your Pan, you muſt bring your right hand between your Pan, and the but-end of your Musket, the Thumb being uppermoſt, and the four Fingers under the guard of your Trig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſo that you may be ready to Fire.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="exercise">
                        <head>12.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Preſent.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>At this word of Command the Pikes muſt charge.</p>
                        <p>You muſt turn your body and advance the right Shoulder even to the left, extend your Arms, and your Musket forward, bringing the but-end of your Musket againſt your breast, your head ſteddy, your eyes upon the Barrel of your Piece, that you may ſee at the end of your Musket, him that you aim at, your elbows muſt be high, and of an equal height.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="exercise">
                        <head>13.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fire.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt draw your Trigger but once and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33947:39"/>keep in the ſame poſture till the following word of Command is given.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="14" type="exercise">
                        <head>14.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>At this word of Command the Pikes muſt advance.</p>
                        <p>You muſt a little draw back your right foot, keep your body upright, and in the ſame poſture, you were before you did preſent.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="exercise">
                        <head>15.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Handle your Match.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt take it in the ſame manner as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but you muſt obſerve to keep the Cole up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and not downward, your Match must be well extended, holding your Match right before your Cravat.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="exercise">
                        <head>16.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Return your Match.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You must return it between the fourth and the ſmall Finger of the left hand, and lay <pb n="65" facs="tcp:33947:40"/>your right hand again on your Musket, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the but-end, and the Pan.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="exercise">
                        <head>17.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Blow your Pan.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring up your Musket, turning your Pan to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards your mouth, and blow but one blast upon it, as you did with your Match.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="18" type="exercise">
                        <head>18.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Handle your Primer.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Take your Primer with your right hand, and carry it to the height of your Cravat, your hand well extended forward.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="19" type="exercise">
                        <head>19.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Prime.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Let fall the Muzzel of your Musket, which you hold with the left hand till it is levelled: you muſt bring your Primer to your Pan, when you prime: you muſt not return your primer till the following word of Command.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="20" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:33947:41"/>
                        <head>20.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Shut your Pan.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt then caſt back your primer, then ſhut your Pan with a full hand: afterwards you muſt lay your hand as before, between the but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end of your Musket and the Pan, your arms being well extended, and your Musket from your body as before.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="21" type="exercise">
                        <head>21.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Blow your Pan.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt bring up your Musket, turning the Pan towards your Mouth: blow upon it once only, as you did with your Match.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="22" type="exercise">
                        <head>22.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Caſt about to charge.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You must extend your Arms, and bring your Musket forwards, caſting the but end of your Musket by your Sword's ſide, advancing your right foot forward, as if your were to turn to the left, ſo your Musket will be on <pb n="69" facs="tcp:33947:42"/>your Swords ſide: your Barrel muſt be down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and the Stock upward, holding your Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket in the left hand with the Muzzle of it, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing raiſed upward.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="23" type="exercise">
                        <head>23.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Handle your Charger.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Take it with your right hand which you muſt bring to the height of your Cravat, your arm being well extended.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="24" type="exercise">
                        <head>24.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Open it with your Teeth.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring it up to your mouth, and open it with your Teeth, and keep it there, till the following word of Command.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="25" type="exercise">
                        <head>25.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge with Powder.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt draw off your Charger, which you have between your Teeth, and bring it up to the muzzle of your Barrel, into which you muſt put your Powder, and keep your Charger <pb n="71" facs="tcp:33947:43"/>in the muzzle till the following word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="26" type="exercise">
                        <head>26.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Draw forth your Scourer.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You must draw it at three motions, and take it with your right hand, your Fingers extended, being drawn, dart it and extend your arm, holding it level, keeping your arm extended: you muſt hold it between your Thumb, and your Fore Finger, the great end of your Scourer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="27" type="exercise">
                        <head>27.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Hold up your Scourer.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt let fall the great end of your Scourer towards your breaſt, a little ſlop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="28" type="exercise">
                        <head>28.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Shorten it againſt your breaſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring the great end of your Scourer againſt your breaſt, bending your arm, ſhorten it to four inches, and hold it ſo till the following word of Command.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="29" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:33947:44"/>
                        <head>29.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Put your Scourer into the Barrel.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring up your Scourer to the muzzle of your Piece, and immediately put it into your Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel: you muſt hold it in your hand, your Thumb being upon the little end of it, and ſo ſtand till the next word of Command.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="30" type="exercise">
                        <head>30.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ram down the Powder.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Ram your Powder three times with your Scourer pretty hard.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="31" type="exercise">
                        <head>31.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Withdraw your Scourer.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>At this word of Command, you muſt quit your Scourer, and take it again, turning your hand outwardly: then draw it as faſt as you can, and dart it level to the height of your Shoulder as before, only the great end muſt be towards your right Shoulder.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="32" type="exercise">
                        <head>32.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Hold up your Scourer.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Turn it as before, but the ſmall end muſt be downward, and the great end upward, and your arm extended.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="33" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:33947:45"/>
                        <head>33.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Shorten it againſt your Breaſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Turn the ſmall end of your Scourer againſt your breaſt, bending your arm, ſlip your hand till within four inches of the end of it, holding it ſo till the following word of Command.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="34" type="exercise">
                        <head>34.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Return your Scourer.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring it within four inches of the muzzle of your Musket, and at the ſame time return it into the Stock of your Musket, then graſp your Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket with your right hand within four inches of the muzzle.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="35" type="exercise">
                        <head>35.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lay your right hand on your Musket.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Truſt the end of your Musket with your right hand, and make it turn level upon the left hand, turning your Wriſt, and at the ſame time graſp your Musket your right hand under the Pan.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="36" type="exercise">
                        <head>36.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Poiſe your Musket.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Raiſe your Musket, and bring it with your right hand before you, turn the right, holding <pb n="75" facs="tcp:33947:46"/> 
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="77" facs="tcp:33947:47"/>the Lock of your Musket at the height of your Cravat.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="37" type="exercise">
                        <head>37.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Shoulder your Musket.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring your Musket upon your Shoulder, graſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it with your left hand, after you have quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it with your right hand, which you muſt careleſſy ſink along your thigh: this is perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by bringing your right foot towards your left hand and turning to the left, and ſo you find your ſelf in the ſame poſture that you were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the firſt Command.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. V. The Exerciſe of the Pikes, explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Motions.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="exercise">
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Order your Pikes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>LAy your left hand on your Pike even with your Shoulder, then quit the but-end of your Pike, which you held in your right hand, which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33947:48"/>hand you muſt bring up above the left, ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Pike and your hand to the height of your waſte; at the ſame time you muſt raiſe your hand even with your eye; when you ſink your Pike, you muſt let it ſlip along your right ſide, without touching it; being on the ground, the but-end of your Pike muſt be cloſe to the latchet of your Shoo, holding it ſo, as if it was glewed to it when your wheel to the right, or to the left, your elbow downward, and your arm ſtretched up along your Pike.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="exercise">
                        <head>2.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>To the right.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Turn a quarter turn to the right, moving your right foot, and turning upon the left: this word of Command is given four times.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="exercise">
                        <head>3.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>To the left.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do, as before in the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which is to turn a quarter turn to the right, only you muſt turn to the left: but turn alwaies upon the ſame foot.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="80" facs="tcp:33947:49"/>
                        <head>4.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>To the right about.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt to obſerve that word of Command, turn half a turn to the right, turning your face where your back was.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="exercise">
                        <head>5.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is the ſame thing as to the right about; only you muſt return as you were by the left.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="exercise">
                        <head>6.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>To the left about.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above in the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: only you muſt turn upon the left.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="exercise">
                        <head>7.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above; only you muſt return as you were by the right.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="exercise">
                        <head>8.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Advance your Pikes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Raiſe your Pike with the right hand that you hold it, and ſtretching up your arm, take your Pike with your left hand to the height of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33947:50"/>your waste: then raiſe your Pike ſo, that you may take the but-end of it in your right hand, and bring it cloſe to your right ſhoulder.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="exercise">
                        <head>9.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the Front.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring your left hand even to your ſhoulder; take your Pike and carry it right before you, extending your arms; advancing a little your right foot, then fall back with your right leg and arm, holding the but end of the Pike in the palm of your hand, bring down your Pike along your left arm, between your Thumb, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Finger of your left hand, your left arm croſs your belly, your elbow forward, and your wriſts towards your right hand.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="exercise">
                        <head>10.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the right.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt raiſe your Pike, and extend your arms, advancing your right foot, and your Pike forward, then turn to the right, and charge as above, in the ninth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, <pb n="85" facs="tcp:33947:51"/>this word of Command is given four times.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="exercise">
                        <head>11.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the right about.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You must do as above in the tenth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: but inſtead of turning a quarter turn to the right, you muſt turn half a turn to the right, ſo that your face may be where your back was.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="exercise">
                        <head>12.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above in the eleventh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; only you muſt return as you were by left.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="exercise">
                        <head>13.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the left.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above in the tenth Command; bu inſtead of turning to the right, you muſt turn to the left: this word of Command must alſo be given four times.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="14" type="exercise">
                        <head>14.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the left about.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You must do as above in the eleventh <pb n="87" facs="tcp:33947:52"/>Command: only you muſt turn half a turn to the left.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="exercise">
                        <head>15.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Return as you were by the right: and you must obſerve, that when the words of Command for handling the Pike have no expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, you muſt do as above in the ninth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="exercise">
                        <head>16.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Shoulder your Pike.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To ſhoulder your Pike, you muſt, your Pike being advanced, lay your left hand on your Pike even to your Shoulder, then quit the but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end of it, draw back your right foot and hand ſtretching your arm to receive the Pike, which you muſt bring to your right Shoulder, the but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end a foot from the ground.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="exercise">
                        <head>17.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the Front.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Stretch your arm, and draw your foot and Pike back, then. lay your left hand on the Pike, and turn it upon that hand which is neareſt to the but end of it, forſaking it with <pb n="89" facs="tcp:33947:53"/>your right hand, to take hold of the but-end, and charge: it muſt lie along upon your left arm, between your Thumb and fore finger, which is called the Fork.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="18" type="exercise">
                        <head>18.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Shoulder as you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above in the ſixteenth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; only you muſt bring your foot and hand forward, and ſhoulder your Pike.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="19" type="exercise">
                        <head>19.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the right.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Charge as before in the ſeventeenth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: after you have carried your Pike back, raiſe it with your right hand, bring the but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end of it forward, turning your body and right foot, take hold of the but-end with your right hand, and charge.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="20" type="exercise">
                        <head>20.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Shoulder as you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring your Pike as before you charged; that is, you muſt bring the but-end of it, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <pb n="91" facs="tcp:33947:54"/>it, and bringing your right foot to the left, as if you were to turn a quarter turn to the left, ſtretching your arm and hand to receive the Pike: afterwards, turn to the left, to lay it on your ſhoulder, as it was before.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="21" type="exercise">
                        <head>21.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the right about.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring your Pike as before in the Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Command: but when your Pike is back, you muſt turn to the left, bringing the but-end of your Pike before you; then taking it with your right hand, charge.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="22" type="exercise">
                        <head>22.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above, when you turned to the right about, only you muſt return as you were, by the left.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="23" type="exercise">
                        <head>23.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the left.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above in the nineteenth Command: but after you are fallen back with <pb n="93" facs="tcp:33947:55"/>your Pike, bring it over your head, bringing your right foot as above, as if you were to turn to the left.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="24" type="exercise">
                        <head>24.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To return as you were, you muſt bring your Pike again over your head, turning to the right; the rest as above in the Seventeenth Command.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="25" type="exercise">
                        <head>25.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the left about.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above in the Seventeenth and three and twentieth Command: all the difference there is, is only that in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you muſt turn half a turn inſtead of a quarter turn.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="26" type="exercise">
                        <head>26.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is the ſame as above in the four and twentieth Command, inſtead of a quarter turn, you muſt turn half a turn.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="27" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:33947:56"/>
                        <head>27.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Comport.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To obſerve this word of Command, from ſhoulder, you muſt lay your left hand on your Pike, which you hold upon your ſhoulder with your left hand, then raiſing it, draw back your foot a little of the ſame ſide carrying your Pike back: then thruſt it back with your left hand, turning your Pike forward with your right hand, ſo that it may fall under your arm the Spear formoſt; then, turn to the left.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="28" type="exercise">
                        <head>28.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the Front.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To obſerve this word of Command, you muſt advance your Pike, your arm and right foot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: then lay your left hand on your Pike, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween your body and right hand, and forſaking it with that hand, take hold of the but-end of it, carrying it back, and your right foot, your left arm croſs your belly, your Pike lying along upon the fork of your left hand, as above in the ninth Command.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="29" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="97" facs="tcp:33947:57"/>
                        <head>29.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Advance the right foot, forſaking the but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end of your Pike, which you hold in your right hand; carry it forward, without moving the left hand, then take hold of your Pike with your right hand, and lay it under your arm; your right foot even with the left.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="30" type="exercise">
                        <head>30.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the right.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Advance your Pike, your arm, and right foot forward: lay your hand on your Pike, between the right ſide and the hand you hold it by; then forſake it with your right to bring it to the but-end of it, drawing back your right foot. You muſt obſerve that your Pike being as if you were to charge to the Front, as ſoon as you bring it to that poſture to raiſe it, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying it forward your arms extended, the right foot to your left instep; but at the ſame time
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ou must turn to the right, and charge.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="31" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="99" facs="tcp:33947:58"/>
                        <head>31.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To return as you were, having charged to the right, raiſe your Pike, extend your arm, turn to the left, forſake the but-end of your Pike backward, which you held in your right hand: then advance your foot, and right hand forward, to take hold of your Pike, to bring it back with your arm, ſetting your foot as if you were to turn to the left, ſo that you find your ſelf with your Pike forward, under your right arm, one foot even with the other.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="32" type="exercise">
                        <head>32.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the right about.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt obſerve, that this word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is the ſame, as when you turn to the right; only in ſtead of turning a quarter turn, you muſt turn half a turn, and the reſt as a bove in the nine and twentieth Command.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="33" type="exercise">
                        <head>33.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above in the two and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33947:59"/>Command, only you muſt return as you were by the left.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="34" type="exercise">
                        <head>34.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the left.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This word of Command, is the ſame with the nine and twentieth, but in ſtead of turning to the right, you muſt turn to the left.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="35" type="exercise">
                        <head>35.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above, as when you turn to the left, only you must return as you were by the right.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="36" type="exercise">
                        <head>36.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the left about.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This Command is the ſame as when you turn to the right about: all the difference is, that you muſt turn to the left about. See above the nine and twentieth Command.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="37" type="exercise">
                        <head>37.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above, when you turn to the left, in the ſix and thirtieth Command, only you muſt return as you-were by the right.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="38" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="103" facs="tcp:33947:60"/>
                        <head>38.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dart your Pike.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To perform this word of Command from Comport, you muſt caſt back your arm, and Pike, turning to the right: turn your Pike paſſing your Fingers under, ſo that your Pike may lie upon your hand to receive it, between your Thumb and Fore finger, the Spear formoſt; you muſt bring it forward turning to the left.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="39" type="exercise">
                        <head>39.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the Front.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To perform this word of Command you muſt advance your right foot forward, bringing your right hand and Pike over your head, take hold of your Pike, with your left hand between the but-end, and your right hand, bringing it before you, turning to the right, taking the but-end of the Pike in the palm of your right hand to charge.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="40" type="exercise">
                        <head>40.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To return as you were, you muſt bring your
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:33947:61"/>Pike forward again, advancing your right foot and body at one motion: then quit the but-end which you held in your right hand, take hold again of your Pike, above your left hand, and bring it again over your head, to bring your ſelf in the ſame poſture as you were when you charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Front.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="41" type="exercise">
                        <head>41.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the right about.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt obſerve, that this word of Command differs much from the others, becauſe that in stead of turning two quarter turns, you muſt turn three quarter turns: to perform it well, you muſt caſt back your Pike, ſtretch that arm you hold it with, ſtepping with your right foot that way that you caſt your Pike, ſtretching your arm ſo, that your Pike falls between your thumb, and ſecond finger: then turn to the right, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Pike over your head, turning your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Finger, Thumb, and the three other Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers over your Pike; afterwards extend your arm, advancing your Pike along your right arm, the Spear alſo to the right: you muſt ſtill keep your eye upon the Spear of your Pike, and <pb n="107" facs="tcp:33947:62"/>lay your left hand between the but end of your Pike, and your right hand, raiſing your Pike, and turning it let it fall upon the left hand, tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hold with your right hand of the but end, then charge.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="42" type="exercise">
                        <head>42.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To return as you were, after you have turn'd to the right, you muſt turn to the left about; obſerving the following motions; turn to the right, raiſing your Pike with your left hand, quitting the but-end, which you hold with your right hand, turn your Pike, and lay it along your right arm, you muſt lay it in your hand, the ſecond finger above the other, bend your Wriſt, turn it inward, your nail upward; then turning to the left, bring your Pike over your head, extend your arm, advancing the but end of your Pike towards your right foot, ſo that you may bring at one motion forward your foot to the Pike, turning to the left, ſo that the Pike be upon your Shoulder, the Spear forward between <pb n="109" facs="tcp:33947:63"/>the Thumb, and ſecond Finger, which we call the fork.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="43" type="exercise">
                        <head>43.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the left.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Step forward with your right foot, and the hand you hold your Pike with, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it over your head, your arm extended, and your Pike forward, lay your hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the but-end, and your right hand, raiſe the Pike before you, then lay your hand on the but-end, and advance your right foot, as you would turn to the right, then charge to the left.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="44" type="exercise">
                        <head>44.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above, when you turn to the left as in the forty third Command, only you muſt return as you were, by the right.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="45" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="111" facs="tcp:33947:64"/>
                        <head>45.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the left about.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This Command is the ſame as when you turn to the left, all the difference is, that you must turn to the left about.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="46" type="exercise">
                        <head>46.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above when you turn to the left, in the five and fortieth Command, only you must return as you were by the right.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="47" type="exercise">
                        <head>47.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Advance your Pike.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring your Pike over your head advanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your foot, your right hand, and your Pike forward, bringing the left hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the but-end of your Pike, and your right hand: then raiſe it bringing your right hand to the but-end, and turning to the right: then lay your Pike againſt your right Shoulder, extend your arms, and let your left hand fall careleſly along your thigh.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="48" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="113" facs="tcp:33947:65"/>
                        <head>48.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the Horſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring your left hand to your Pike, even to your Shoulder, then bring it forward, advancing both your arms and your right foot, quitting the but end of your Pike: then bring your right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand above the left, ſink your Pike, bringing the but-end of it cloſe to the lachet of your left ſhoo, your right foot muſt be forward, bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your body upon your right thigh, and the Spear of your Pike to the height of the horſe's poitrel.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="49" type="exercise">
                        <head>49.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Draw your Swords.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring your right hand over your Pike and left arm, with which you draw your Sword, then bring it croſs upon your Pike, your arm extended.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="50" type="exercise">
                        <head>50.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Return your Swords.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Draw back a little your foot and Pike, bringing your Sword, and right arm under it: thon quit your Pike, which you hold in the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33947:66"/>left hand, laying it upon the right arm, take the Scabbard with your left hand, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn your Sword with more eaſe; then take hold of your Pike with both hands, at two foot diſtance.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="51" type="exercise">
                        <head>51.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Advance your Pike.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Draw your right foot even with the other, bring up your body ſtreight, raiſing your Pike with the right hand, ſlipping it into the left, quit the top of your Pike, which you held in your right hand, which hand you muſt bring to the but-end: then lay it againſt your right ſhoulder, your left arm along your thigh.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="52" type="exercise">
                        <head>52.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Charge to the Front.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt do as above in the ninth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="53" type="exercise">
                        <head>53.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>March.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Step forward with your right foot, and take heed you do not ſtep more forward then the reſt; you muſt always caſt your eyes to the right <pb n="117" facs="tcp:33947:67"/>and left, without bending your body of either ſide.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="54" type="exercise">
                        <head>54.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Halt.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Stop all at once, as if you were all link'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="55" type="exercise">
                        <head>55.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Puſh your Pikes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To puſh your Pike well, your muſt ſtretch your arm ſtrongly, not toſſing the Spear: but puſhing it streight to the body of him you aim at: you muſt bring the but-end near your left ſhoulder, you must puſh and draw back, as faſt as you can, that your strokes may be quick.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="56" type="exercise">
                        <head>56.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Trail.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt quit the but end of your Pike, fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the right about,</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="57" type="exercise">
                        <pb n="119" facs="tcp:33947:68"/>
                        <head>57.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>March.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Step with your right foot forward, and march till the word of Command, <hi>Halt,</hi> is given.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="58" type="exercise">
                        <head>58.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As you were.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt return as you were before, facing to the left, taking hold of the but-end of your Pike with your right hand.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="59" type="exercise">
                        <head>59.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Advance your Pike.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bring your right foot even with the other: ſtretch your arms, and bring your Pike forward: then bring it to your right ſhoulder, your left arm along your thigh.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:33947:69"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VI. The Exerciſe of the Foot.</head>
                     <p>WHen you have drawn up your Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Battalia, you muſt Command ſilence to be obſerved, and your Soldiers to carry their arms well.</p>
                     <div type="commands">
                        <head>Then you Command the Battalion to open their Files.</head>
                        <p>Take heed to open your Files. Let the right hand File ſtand.</p>
                        <p>To the left, Open your Files at a pace di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
                        <p>March.</p>
                        <p>Halt.</p>
                        <p>To the reght.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:33947:70"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VII. The Exerciſe of the Musket.</head>
                     <p>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>sketeers, have a care of the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</p>
                     <p>Lay your right hand on your Musket.</p>
                     <p>Poiſe your Musket.</p>
                     <p>Reſt your Musket.</p>
                     <p>Handle your Match.</p>
                     <p>Blow your Match.</p>
                     <p>Cock your Match.</p>
                     <p>Try your Match.</p>
                     <p>Guard your Pan with your two fore-fingers.</p>
                     <p>Blow your Match.</p>
                     <p>Open your Pan.</p>
                     <p>Preſent: <hi>At this word of Command the Pikes muſt charge.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fire.</p>
                     <p>Recover your Arms. <hi>At this word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Pikes muſt advance.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:33947:71"/>
                     <p>Handle your Match.</p>
                     <p>Return your Match.</p>
                     <p>Blow your Pan.</p>
                     <p>Handle you Primer.</p>
                     <p>Prime.</p>
                     <p>Shut your Pan.</p>
                     <p>Blow your Pan.</p>
                     <p>Caſt about to Charge.</p>
                     <p>Handle your Charger.</p>
                     <p>Open it with your Teeth.</p>
                     <p>Charge with Powder.</p>
                     <p>Draw forth your Scourer.</p>
                     <p>Hold up your Scourer.</p>
                     <p>Shorten it againſt your breaſt.</p>
                     <p>Put your Scourer. in your Barrel.</p>
                     <p>Ram down.</p>
                     <p>Recover your Scourer.</p>
                     <p>Hold up your Scourer.</p>
                     <p>Shorten it againſt your breaſt.</p>
                     <p>Return your Scourer.</p>
                     <p>Lay your right hand to your Musket.</p>
                     <p>Poiſe your Musket.</p>
                     <p>Shoulder your Musket.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:33947:72"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VIII. The Exerciſe of the Pike.</head>
                     <p>PIkes, take heed.</p>
                     <p>Pikes, to your outſide order.</p>
                     <p>To the right, to the right, to the right, to the right.</p>
                     <p>To the right about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>To the left, to the left, to the left, to the left.</p>
                     <p>To the left about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Advance your Pike.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the Front.</p>
                     <p>To the right, to the right, to the right, to the right.</p>
                     <p>To the right about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>To the left, to the left, to the left, to the left.</p>
                     <p>To the left about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:33947:73"/>
                     <p>Advance your Pike.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the Front.</p>
                     <p>To the right, to the right, to the right, to the right.</p>
                     <p>To the right about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>To the left, to the left, to the left, to the left.</p>
                     <p>To the left about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Advance your Pike.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the Front.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the right.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the right about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the left.</p>
                     <p>As you were,</p>
                     <p>Charge to the left about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Shoulder your Pike.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the Front.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the right.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:33947:74"/>
                     <p>Charge to the right about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the left.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the left about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Advance your Pike.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the Front.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Advance your Pike.</p>
                     <p>Comport.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the Front.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the right.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the right about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the left.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the left about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Dart your Pike.</p>
                     <pb n="133" facs="tcp:33947:75"/>
                     <p>Charge to the Front.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the right.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the right about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the left.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the left about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Advance your Pike.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the Horſe.</p>
                     <p>Draw your Swords.</p>
                     <p>To the right, to the right, to the right, to the right.</p>
                     <p>To the right about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>To the left, to the left, to the left, to the left.</p>
                     <p>To the left about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Return your Swords.</p>
                     <p>Advance your Pike.</p>
                     <p>Charge to the Front.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <p>Puſh your Pike.</p>
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:33947:76"/>
                     <p>Trail.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Advance your Pike.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IX. Exerciſe of the whole Battalion.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>TAke heed all the Battalion to preſent their Arms.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Musketeers make ready.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>At that time the Pikemen Charge.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, to the right, to the right, to the right,</p>
                     <p>To the right about</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>To the left, to the left, to the left, to the left.</p>
                     <p>To the left about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>Handle your Match,</p>
                     <p>Return your Match.</p>
                     <p>Shoulder your Musket.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>At that time the Pikes advance.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:33947:77"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take heed all the Battalion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, to the right, to the right, to the right.</p>
                     <p>To the right about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>To the left, to the left, to the left, to the left.</p>
                     <p>To the left about.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ranks that are to double, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Double to the Front.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the left, Ranks double to the Front.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ranks that have not doubled, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, double your Ranks to the Rear.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Ranks as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the left, double your Ranks to the Rear.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:33947:78"/>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half File-Leaders, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right by half File-Leaders, double to the Front.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By Bringers-up, Ranks as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the left by half File-Leaders, double your Ranks to the Front.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By Bringers-up, Ranks as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bringers-up of half Files, take heed:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, by Bringers up of half Files, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your Ranks to the Rear.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By File-Leaders, Ranks as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the left, by Bringers-up of half Files, Ranks double to the Rear.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By half File Leaders, Ranks as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bringers-up take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:33947:79"/>
                     <p>To the right, by Bringers-up, Ranks, double to the Front.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By half File-Leaders, Ranks as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the left by Bringers up, Ranks double to the Front.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By half File-Leaders. Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>File-Leaders, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, by File-Leaders, Ranks double to the Rear.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the right about, March.</p>
                     <p>To the left about, March.</p>
                     <p>By Bringers-up of half Files, Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the left, by File Leaders, Ranks, double to the Rear.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half Ranks, take heed to bring up your Files.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by half Ranks bring up your Files.</p>
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:33947:80"/>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half File-Leaders, take heed to double to the Front upon the Flanks.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left by half File Leaders dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Front upon the Flanks.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By Bringers up, Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bringers up of half Files, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by Bringers-up of half Files Ranks, double to the Rear upon the Flanks.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By File Leaders, Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half File Leaders, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left by half File Leaders, Ranks double to the Front and inward.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half Ranks, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left by half Ranks, return to your diſtance.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:33947:81"/>
                     <p>To the right and left.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Files, that are to double, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, double your Files; March.</p>
                     <p>To the right, treble your Files, March.</p>
                     <p>Files, as you were, March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Files that have not doubled take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the left, double your Files, March.</p>
                     <p>To the left, treble your Files, March.</p>
                     <p>Treble your Files, March.</p>
                     <p>Files, as you were, March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half Ranks, take heed to double your Files.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right by half Ranks, double your Files.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Half Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half Ranks, that have not doubled, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the left, by half Ranks, double your Files</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Half Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:33947:82"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half Ranks take heed to double your Files to the Front, and to the Rear.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, by half Ranks double your Files to the Front, and to the Rear. March.</p>
                     <p>Half Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half Ranks that have not doubled take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the left, by half Ranks, double your Files to the Front, and to the Rear.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Half Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half Ranks, take heed to double your Files inward.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right by half Ranks, double your Files inward, March.</p>
                     <p>Half Ranks, as you were. March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half Ranks, that have not doubled take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the left, by half Files, Ranks double your Files inward.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Half Ranks as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:33947:83"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarter Ranks, take heed to double your Files.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right by quarter Ranks, double your Files.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarter Ranks, that have not doubled, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the left, by quarter Ranks, double your Files.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Flanks, quarter Ranks, take heed to dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your Files upon the Center quarter Ranks.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, and left by Flanks quarter Ranks double your Files upon the Center quarter Ranks.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Center quarter Ranks take heed to double
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:33947:84"/>your Files, upon the Flank quarter Ranks.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by Center quarter Ranks, double your Files, upon the Flanks quarters Ranks.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Ranks as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarter Ranks take heed to double your Files to the Front and to the Rear.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right by quarter Ranks, double your Files to the Front and to the Rear.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarter Ranks, that have not doubled, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the left by quarter Ranks, double your Files to the Front, and to the Rear.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Flanks, quarter Ranks, take heed to double your Files upon the Center, quarter</hi> 
                        <pb n="153" facs="tcp:33947:85"/>Ranks to the Front, and to the Rear.</p>
                     <p>To the right, and left, by Flank quarter Ranks, double your Files upon the Center, quarter Ranks to the Front and to the Rear.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Center quarter Ranks, take heed to double your Files upon the Flank quarter Ranks to the Front and Rear.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by Center quarter Ranks, double your Files upon the Flank quarter Ranks to the Front and Rear.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarter Ranks, take heed to double your Files inward.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right by quarter Ranks, double your Files inward.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarter Ranks that have not doubled take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:33947:86"/>
                     <p>To the left by quarter Ranks, double your Files inward.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Flanks quarter Ranks take heed to double your Files upon the Center quarter Ranks inward.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by Flank quarter Ranks, double your Files upon the Center quarter Ranks inward.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Center quarter Ranks, take heed to double your Files, upon the Flank quarter Ranks inward.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by Center quarter Ranks, double your Files upon the Flank quarter Ranks inward.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="157" facs="tcp:33947:87"/>
                     <head>CHAP. X. The manner how to interchange ground.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>TAke heed all the Battalion to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change ground.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right by Ranks, interchange ground.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <p>To the left.</p>
                     <p>To the left by Ranks, interchange ground.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <p>To the right.</p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by half Ranks inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change ground.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <p>To the right and left.</p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by quarter Ranks inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change ground. March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <pb n="159" facs="tcp:33947:88"/>
                     <p>To the right and left.</p>
                     <p>To the right by Files, interchange ground.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <p>To the right about.</p>
                     <p>To the left by Files, interchange ground.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halte.</p>
                     <p>To the left about.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XI. Of the manner of Wheelings.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>TAke heed all the Battalion, to Wheel to the right or left.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Wheel to the right.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <p>Wheel to the left.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:33947:89"/>
                     <p>Reſt upon your Arms. <hi>The Pikes muſt be to their outſide order.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Lay down your Arms. <hi>The Pikemen muſt lay down their Pikes between their Feet; in ſome places they lay them down on the right ſide: I do not blame their way, but we muſt always find out the eaſieſt and the quickeſt way.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right about, and to the left about, break the Battalion.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To your Arms.</p>
                     <p>Handle your Arms.</p>
                     <p>Shoulder your muskets. The Pikemen muſt alſo ſhoulder their Pikes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XII. The Exerciſe by quarter Files.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THe Battalion muſt be eight deep, and the following word of Command muſt be given.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="163" facs="tcp:33947:90"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarter files, take heed to double your Ranks to the Front.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, by quarter files, double your Ranks to the Front, March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the left, by quarter Files, double your Ranks to the Front, March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quarter Files, take heed to double your Ranks to the Rear.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right by quarter Files, double your Ranks to the Rear, March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the left, by quarter Files, double your Ranks to the Rear, March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half File Leaders take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, by Half File Leaders, double your Ranks to the Front. March.</p>
                     <p>By Bringers up, as you were.</p>
                     <pb n="165" facs="tcp:33947:91"/>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the left, by half File Leaders, double your Ranks to the Front, March.</p>
                     <p>By Bringers up, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bringers-up, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, by Bringers up of half Files, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your Ranks on the Rear, March.</p>
                     <p>By File Leaders, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the left, by Bringers-up of half Files, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your Ranks on the Rear, March.</p>
                     <p>By File Leaders, as you were. March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Front and Rear, quarter Files, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right by Front and Rear quarter Files, double your Ranks to the Front, and to the</p>
                     <p>Rear, upon the Center quarter Files.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the left, by Front and Rear quarter Files, double your Ranks to the Front and to the Rear, upon the Center Quarter Files.</p>
                     <pb n="167" facs="tcp:33947:92"/>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Center quarter Files, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, by Center quarter Files double your Ranks to the Front and to the Rear, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Front and Rear quarter Files.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the left, by Center quarter Files, double your Ranks to the Front and to the Rear, upon the Front and Rear quarter Files.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half Ranks, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by half Ranks cloſe your Files.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take heed to double your Ranks to the Front upon the Flanks.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, and left, by quarter Files, double your Ranks to the Front upon the Flanks.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:33947:93"/>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by quarter Files, double your Ranks to the Rear, upon the Flanks.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by quarter Ranks, double to the Front inward.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by quarter Files, double your Ranks to the Rear inward.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By quarter Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half File Leaders, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by half File Leaders, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your Ranks to the Front upon the Flanks.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By Bringers-up, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bringers-up of half Files, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="171" facs="tcp:33947:94"/>
                     <p>To the right and left, by Bringers up of half Files, double your Ranks to the Rear, upon the Flanks. March.</p>
                     <p>By Bringers-up, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bringers up of half Files, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by Bringers up of half Files, double your Ranks on the Rear in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward upon the Flanks.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By File-Leaders, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Half File Leaders, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by half File Leaders double your Ranks to the Front inward.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By Bringers up, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bringers-up of half Files, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by Bringers up of half Files, double your Ranks on the Rear inward.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>By File Leaders, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <pb n="173" facs="tcp:33947:95"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Front and Rear quarter Files, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by Front and Rear, quarter Files, double your Ranks to the Front and Rear, upon the Center quarter Files up on the Flanks, March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Center quarter Files, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by Center quarter Files, double your Ranks to the Front and Rear, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Front and Rear quarter Files upon the Flanks, March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Front and Rear quarter Files, take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by Front and Rear quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Files, double your Ranks to the Rear, upon the Center quarter Files inward.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Center quarter Files take heed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="175" facs="tcp:33947:96"/>
                     <p>To the right and left, by Center quarter Files, double your Ranks to the Front, and to the Rear, upon the Front and Rear quarter Files inward.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Quarter Files, as you were.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by half Ranks, return to your diſtances.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pikemen take heed to fraize the Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right and left, by whole Ranks of Pikes fraize the Battalion by the Front and Rear.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <p>To the right and left.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <p>To the right and left.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take heed to return as you were.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the right, and left Ranks, as you were.</p>
                     <pb n="177" facs="tcp:33947:97"/>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <p>To the right and left.</p>
                     <p>March.</p>
                     <p>Halt.</p>
                     <p>As you were.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XIII. Of the manner how to behave your ſelves in all ſorts of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files.</head>
                     <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> muſt take care in all Defiles, that the Files be alwayes odd: and when you find ſupernumerary Files, you muſt form a Rank of them to the Rear of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                     <p>Obſerve when the Diviſions File off, that in the places where you are to wheel to the right, or left, the Ranks turn to the place where the firſt Rank hath turned, taking <pb n="179" facs="tcp:33947:98"/>care to follow your File Leader, ſtep by ſtep.</p>
                     <p>To that end, the Serjeants of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion muſt ſtop at the place where it is to wheel, till the laſt Rank is paſt, and hath Filed off.</p>
                     <p>When you File off upon a Bridge before the Enemy, after the detach'd men have paſt, you muſt make the Battalion File off by Ranks from the Center. You muſt wheel to the right or left, or to the right or left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XIV. Of the manner of Firing.</head>
                     <p>THE beſt way of Firing is by Ranks, when you intend to Fire in a parallel Line to the Enemy.</p>
                     <p>To that end, to Fire without confuſion, you muſt Fire, ſtanding firm upon your feet <pb n="181" facs="tcp:33947:99"/>without any other motion than making kneel the five firſt Ranks; and the ſixth Rank is to Fire firſt: the fifth getting up doth the ſame, and ſo the reſt. The Ranks, before the skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh begins again, are to be cloſe at two paces distance.</p>
                     <p>When you are to bear the Enemies fire by Detached men, either in the Paſs of a River, Hollow way, or retreating, you muſt detach by Files from the right and left of Musketeers, who ſhall be led without intermiſſion by Officers appointed for that purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>And ſo coming back to their poſt, they ſhall be led to it, by the ſame Officers.</p>
                     <p>When you march by Diviſions to form a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the Battalion, marching for the greater facility, you muſt firſt double in three bodies, two of Musketeers, and one of Pikes: and afterwards, without loſing time, joyn the thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> bodies together.</p>
                     <p>In making theſe motions, the Front muſt
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:33947:100"/>ſtep but ſlowly, to give time to thoſe that double, to joyn the Front without precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>You may alſo File off, marching after the ſame manner, obſerving alſo, that the Front muſt move faster: and that notwithſtanding the Battalion marches continually with a ſlower pace without making any Halt.</p>
                     <p>When the Regiment is in Battalia, and that you will make the Companies File off, to lay down their arms, or to return to their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, you must march the two Wings of Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keteers, and the Pikes are to ſtay behind, ſo that the ſaid Wings of Musketeers cloſing to the right and left, may joyn upon that ground, which ſhall be neceſſary, to give way to the Pikemen to be each at the Rear of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Company: after which, each Company Files off, without loſing time, and each Officer in his proper post.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33947:101"/>
                  <head>The Table of the Chapters.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>THE Major's Duty, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>Page.</hi> 3</item>
                     <item>The Manner and the Terms of a Battalion, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.
<hi>Page.</hi> 15</item>
                     <item>The general Exerciſe of the Foot, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.
<hi>Page.</hi> 44</item>
                     <item>The Exerciſe of the Muſquet, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.
<hi>Page.</hi> 51</item>
                     <item>The Exerciſe of the Pike explained by motions,
<hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>Page.</hi> 77</item>
                     <item>The Exerciſe of the Foot, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.
<hi>Page.</hi> 121</item>
                     <item>The Exerciſe of the Muſquet, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.
<hi>Page.</hi> 123</item>
                     <item>The Exerciſe of the Pike, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.
<hi>Page.</hi> 127</item>
                     <item>The Exerciſe of the whole Battalion, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.
<hi>Page.</hi> 135</item>
                     <item>The manner how to interchange ground, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.
<hi>Page.</hi> 157</item>
                     <item>Of the manner of Wheelings, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.
<hi>Page.</hi> 159</item>
                     <item>The Exerciſe by quarter Files, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.
<hi>Page.</hi> 161</item>
                     <item>The manner how to behave your ſelves in all ſorts of Defiles, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. <hi>Page.</hi> 177</item>
                     <item>Of the manner of Firings, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. <hi>Page.</hi>
179</item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
